<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Gentlemen and Ladies' Town and Country Magazine</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published by the American Antiquarian Society's Just Teach One Initiative.</p>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <ref type="catalog-url">http://catalog.mwa.org/vwebv/holdingsInfo?bibId=15579</ref>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>
                <bibl style="font­-style: italic">The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</bibl>,
                published in <bibl style="font­-style: italic">The Gentlemen and Ladies' Town and
                  Country Magazine</bibl>, <date when="1789-06">June 1789</date> to <date
                  when="1791-01">January 1791</date>
                <placeName>Boston, MA</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Nathaniel Coverly</persName>
              </publisher>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.01">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-06"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 5</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.02">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-07"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 6</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.03">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-08"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 7</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.04">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-09"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 8</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.05">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-10"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 9</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.06">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-11"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 10</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.07">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1789-12"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 11</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

      <sourceDesc xml:id="15579.08">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Story of Constantius and Pulchera</title>
            <idno type="aas">15579</idno>
            <imprint>
              <date when="1790-01"/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <series>
            <biblScope>Volume 1, Number 12</biblScope>
          </series>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text corresp="#15579">
    <front>
      <titlePage style="text-align:center">
        <titlePart type="desc">The STORY of <persName>CONSTANTIUS</persName> and <lb/><seg
            xml:id="a001" corresp="#n001"><persName>PULCHERA</persName>.</seg><note xml:id="n001"
            corresp="#a001">This first installment, in <date when="1789-06">June of 1789</date>,
            appeared with the following heading: “<hi rend="italic">For the </hi><bibl>GENTLEMEN <hi
                rend="italic">and</hi> LADIES MAGAZINE</bibl>. <persName>Mr. COVERLY</persName>, <hi
              rend="italic">If you think the following authentick Story worthy a place in your
              entertaining Magazine, you’ll please to insert it in your fifth number.</hi>” After
            the title, there appeared a line reading “[<hi rend="italic">Embellished with a fine
              Engraving.</hi>]”</note></titlePart>
      </titlePage>
    </front>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.01">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p>IN the suburbs of the city of <placeName>Phi- <lb break="no"
                />ladelphia</placeName>, in the soft season of the <lb/>year, about one o’clock on a
              moon- <lb/>shining morning, on the terrace of an <lb/>high building, forty feet from
              the <lb/>ground, appeared a most beautiful <lb/>Lady of the age of sixteen—she was
              <lb/>clad in a long white vest, her hair <lb/>of a beautiful chesnut colour hanging
              <lb/>carelessly over her shoulders, every <lb/>mark of greatness was visible in her
              <lb/>countenance, which was overcast with <lb/>a solemn gloom, and now and then,
              <lb/>the unwilling tear unnoticed, rolled <lb/>down her cheek. </p>
            <p> She cast her eyes around, taking a <lb/>survey of the garden below, and the
              <lb/>places adjacent—a fixed melancholy <cb/>
              <lb/>apparently encreased on her counte- <lb break="no"/>nance, and now and then the
              big sigh <lb/>would burst from her labouring bo- <lb break="no"/>som—more than once
              she attempted <lb/>to return into the chamber from <lb/>which she had made her
              appearance— <lb/>and then would appear unresolved— <lb/>At length, taking a chair, and
              seating <lb/>herself near the side of the terrace, <lb/>and after a few moments of
              express- <lb break="no"/>ive silence she thus uttered herself, <lb/>“O
                  <choice><sic>cruel,</sic><corr>cruel</corr></choice> fortune! O more cruel
              <lb/>parent!—when shall I again be- <lb break="no"/>hold my adorable <hi rend="italic"
                  ><persName>Constantius</persName></hi>? but <lb/>why do I mention him? why do I
              re- <lb break="no"/>cal his lov’d ideas? He is gone— <lb/>I am banished forever from
              him, clois- <lb break="no"/>tered up in this unblessed mansion—
                  <lb/><choice><sic>debared</sic><corr>debarred</corr></choice> from him, for whose
              sake <lb/>only I could wish to live!—but I must <lb/>deface his memory.—O for one
              <lb/>draught from the <seg xml:id="a002" corresp="#n002"><placeName>river <hi
                    rend="italic">Lethe</hi></placeName>,</seg><note xml:id="n002" corresp="#a002"
                >In Greek mythology the <placeName>river <hi rend="italic">Lethe</hi></placeName>
                was one of five rivers surrounding Hades, and its waters were believed to cause
                anyone who drank them to experience total loss of memory. Before passing into Hades,
                the dead had to drink from this river to erase all memories of their earthy
                existence.</note> that the <lb/>tender feelings of my distracted bo- <lb break="no"
              />som might no more be harrowed up <lb/>by his recollection! Alas! vain is the
              <lb/>wish, the impression on my heart is so <lb/>deep, that it cannot be defaced but
              by <lb/>annihilation!—can I ever eradicate <lb/>from my mind his lovely features, his
              <lb/>charming disposition, his fine sense, <lb/>with all his finished accomplishments—
              <lb/>No sooner than that could be the case <pb/>
              <lb/>the <seg xml:id="a003" corresp="#n003">adamant</seg><note xml:id="n003"
                corresp="#a003"><term style="font-style: italic">Adamant</term>: a rock or mineral
                of impenetrable hardness.</note> would vegitate. All im- <lb break="no"
              />possibilities will become practicable, <lb/>sooner than I could forget that flood
              <lb/>of transport with which I surrender- <lb break="no"/>ed my heart to him, and took
              delivery <lb/>of his in exchange, and called on <lb/>Heaven to register the
              indissoluble <lb/>contract. </p>
            <p> Oh! the effusion of extacy <lb/>of that happy moment, the soft re- <lb break="no"
              />membrance of which serves no other <lb/>purpose, than to plant daggers in my
              <lb/>distracted bosom. Why should a fa- <lb break="no"/>ther be lost to every tender
              feeling, <lb/>and tear me instantaneously from the <lb/>summit of happiness, and place
              me <lb/>in the <emph style="font­-style: italic">focus</emph> of torment!—“ne- <lb
                break="no"/>ver more to see him!” The cru- <lb break="no"/>elest accents which ever
              were utter- <lb break="no"/>ed by one who is totally unworthy <lb/>the name of “<term
                style="font-style: italic">father</term>”! Has he as- <lb break="no"/>sassinated
              him? or has he procured <lb/>his manumission to some foreign bar- <lb break="no"
              />barous land? O could I but once <lb/>more see him, though it were just <lb/>long
              enough to bid him a final fare- <lb break="no"/>well—O could I but have the
              <lb/>satisfaction of taking my leave of him, <lb/>though it were in the agonies of
              death, <lb/>how would I wash his mangled limbs <lb/>with tears, and kiss the departing
              soul <lb/>from his quivering lips! How would <lb/>my soul burst through the shackles
              of <lb/>its clay tenement, and bear him com- <lb break="no"/>pany through the
              unexplored regions <lb/>of <placeName>Elysian</placeName>! but in vain the wish.—
              <lb/>But what doth my eyes see passing <lb/>through the moon shade of the gar- <lb
                break="no"/>den? It is my dear lov’d <hi rend="italic"><persName>Constanti- <lb
                    break="no"/>us</persName></hi>, or his spirit returned from the <lb/><seg
                xml:id="a004" corresp="#n004"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Elyssiam</hi>
                  fields</placeName>!</seg><note xml:id="n004" corresp="#a004">In Greek mythology,
                the <placeName><term style="font-style: italic">Elysian</term> fields</placeName>
                (also called simply <placeName><term style="font-style: italic"
                  >Elysium</term></placeName>) were the final paradisiacal resting place of gods and
                select human heroes.</note> But hark, I hear <lb/>his <choice><orig>footsteps,
                  </orig><reg>footsteps—</reg></choice>it is he, and not his spi- <lb break="no"
              />rit—Once more have my optic <lb/>nerves reanimated my almost <lb/>deserted body—<hi
                rend="italic"><persName>Constantius</persName>!</hi>
              <hi rend="italic"><persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName>!</hi> once more
              your <hi rend="italic"><persName>Pulchera</persName></hi>
              <lb/>beholds you: my eyes are enchanted <lb/>at the prospect, though bars of iron
              <lb/>hold me from your embraces! Three <lb/>fold bolted doors
                  <choice><sic>secures</sic><corr>secure</corr></choice> me from you <lb/>—yet I
              behold you and never <lb/>more will I complain of adverse for- <lb break="no"/>tune,
              if I can but expire before you <lb/>are taken from my view, Dear <hi rend="italic"
                  ><persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName>!</hi>
              <hi rend="italic"><persName>Constantius</persName>!</hi> He lifted up his <cb/>
              <lb/>eyes and beheld her—with the strong- <lb break="no"/>est emotions of elevated
              joy, he ex- <lb break="no"/>claimed, “my Dear <hi rend="italic"
                      ><persName><choice><sic>Puchera</sic><corr>Pulchera</corr></choice></persName>,</hi>
              it is <lb/>enough! once more I do behold the <lb/>object to which in my mind I had
              giv- <lb break="no"/>en a final adieu!—driven from <lb/>your arms by a father, who
              till the fa- <lb break="no"/>tal moment had expressed his appro- <lb break="no"
              />bation of me in the most flattering <lb/>terms, with a ferocity which I never
              <lb/>before believed human nature capa- <lb break="no"/>ble of, he drove me from his
              house, <lb/>after having torn from me the delight <lb/>of my eyes, and the ravisher of
              my <lb/>heart—tell me my dearest <hi rend="italic"><persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"
                  />ra</persName></hi>, what was the cause of this strange <lb/>alteration of
              conduct in him, whom <lb/>once I thought worthy to be called <lb/>your father. </p>
            <p> The distressed <hi rend="italic"><persName>Pulchera</persName></hi>, replyed,
              <lb/>Ambition! cruel ambition is the <lb/>cause of our misfortune—no man <lb/>was ever
              better pleased with another, <lb/>than my father was with you, until <lb/><seg
                xml:id="a005" corresp="#n005"><persName>Monsieur le Monte</persName>,</seg><note
                xml:id="n005" corresp="#a005"><term style="font-style: italic"><persName>Le
                    Monte</persName></term>: this French name may allude to the verb <term
                  style="font-style: italic">monter</term> (to climb, to mount, to raise) or the
                noun <term style="font-style: italic">mont</term> (mountain).</note> only son and
              <lb/>heir to a rich nobleman in <placeName>France</placeName>, <lb/>waited on him, and
              offered to make <lb/>me his wife, giving a most inchanting
                  <lb/><choice><sic>discription</sic><corr>description</corr></choice> of the
              honours and pomp <lb/>he would advance me to—the <lb/>temptation was too great for him
              to <lb/>withstand—the anticipations of tin- <lb break="no"/>sel’d greatness took full
              possession of <lb/>his soul—he promised Monsieur <lb/>that I should be his—he soon in-
                <lb break="no"/>formed me of my
                  <choice><sic>distination</sic><corr>destination</corr></choice>, and <lb/>I could
              see joy sparkling in his eyes <lb/>when he reflected on the good for- <lb break="no"
              />tune to which he fondly imagined my <lb/>good stars had destined me—In <lb/>vain did
              I remonstrate to him, <lb/>that by his own free and voluntary <lb/>consent I had
              formed an indissoluble <lb/>union with my dearest <hi rend="italic"
                  ><persName>Constantius</persName></hi>, and <lb/>that love had cemented us beyond
              the <lb/>power of separation; and while <lb/>I was going on with my most <lb/>pathetic
              lamentation for his conduct, <lb/>your approach interrupted me—a <lb/>degree of
              rancor, which ’till then <lb/>I supposed him totally incapable of, <lb/>appeared in
              his visage, and your own <lb/>recollection will furnish you with <lb/>ideas of his
              conduct, until he drove <lb/>you from the garden in which we <pb/>
              <lb/>were, and gave you the solemn <lb/>assurances you never should see me <lb/>more. </p>
            <p> He then secured me in the cham- <lb break="no"/>ber communicating with the <seg
                xml:id="a006" corresp="#n006">terrass,</seg><note xml:id="n006" corresp="#a006"
                  ><term style="font-style: italic">Terrass</term>: terrace (French).</note>
              <lb/>on which you see me forty feet <lb/>high, and to-morrow is the day when <lb/>I am
              to embark for <placeName>France</placeName> in a pac- <lb break="no"/>ket,
                  <choice><sic>lyling</sic><corr>lying</corr></choice> in the river, with monsieur,
              <lb/>to be his forever—here her voice <lb/>failed her, and she almost dissolved in a
              <lb/>flood of tears. <hi rend="italic"><persName>Constantius</persName></hi> was on
              <lb/> the rack at this fatal intelligence— <lb/>In despair he drew his sword, and was
              <lb/>on the eve of falling on its point, <lb/>thereby putting a period to an
              <lb/>existence which he no longer could <lb/>consider as a blessing; but fortune
              <lb/>which always favours the virtuous, <lb/>suggested to his mind the idea of a
              <lb/>Tow-line he that day had observed <lb/>in his store, which had been left there
              <lb/>by accident—he cries out <hi rend="italic"><persName>Pulchera</persName></hi>,
              <lb/>be contented a few moments and I <lb/>will relieve you—so running to his
              <lb/>store which stood not far distant, he <lb/>takes the tow-line, and lashing three
              <lb/>oars at the end of each, making <lb/>the rope fast to the end of them, he <lb/>by
              this means communicated the end <lb/>of the rope to <hi rend="italic"
                  ><persName>Pulchera</persName></hi>, who disen- <lb break="no"/>gaged it from the
              oar, made it fast to <lb/>one of the banisters of the terrass, by <lb/>which means she
              descended, though <lb/>the knot by which she made the rope <lb/>fast slipped before
              she had got to the <lb/>ground, yet she was so near it that <lb/>she received no
              material damage <lb/>thereby—never perhaps was joy <lb/>more triumphant than on this
              occasion <lb/>—he straightway conveyed her to his <lb/>chamber where the remainder of
              the <lb/>night was spent in a far more agreeable <lb/>manner than the former part
              thereof had <seg xml:id="a007" corresp="#n007">been.</seg><note xml:id="n007"
                corresp="#a007">Here the first (<date when="1789-06">June</date>) installment ends
                with the notice “[<hi rend="italic">To be continued</hi>.]”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.02">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p> NEVER was there perhaps a <lb/>greater transition from
              doleful <lb/>anticipations to real joy than had <lb/>been experienced by
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>; for <lb/>nothing could be more distressing to
              <lb/>her than the idea of being forever <lb/>separated from her
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, to <lb/>be forced by cruel parental authority
              <lb/>from her home, her friends, and from <lb/>every pleasing prospect, into a foreign
              <lb/>land, and there to be shackled for <lb/>life to a man to whom she had the
              <lb/>most fixed and irreversable aversion, <lb/>and from whom she had no conceiva- <lb
                break="no"/>ble way to escape than through the <lb/>avenue of death; thus
              circumstanced, <lb/>to be in a manner bordering on the <lb/>invisible world, and
              divested of all <lb/>her fearful apprehensions, at the same <lb/>time to find herself
              in the full posses- <lb break="no"/>sion of him who was dearer to her <lb/>than all
              things else, was well nigh too <lb/>hard for her. They scarcely had <lb/>finished
              their reciprocal congratula- <lb break="no"/>tions, when the clock advertised them
              <lb/>that two hours of the last half of the <lb/>night were expended, when
                <persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName> informed her that her safety re-
                <lb break="no"/>quired her to be put in some place <lb/>more secure from the
              researches of <lb/>her father, who would doubtless make <lb/>the most vigorous efforts
              to recover <lb/>her. This piece of information gave <lb/>a most surprising shock to
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, <lb/>who till that moment had considered <lb/>herself
              in the most perfect security; <lb/>various schemes of safety were pro- <lb break="no"
              />posed by each of them, not one of <lb/>which on examination proved admis- <lb
                break="no"/>sible, at length the dawn of day ap- <lb break="no"/>proaching,
              necessity obliged them to <lb/>leave their present place of retreat, <lb/>and conclude
              on some place of secu- <lb break="no"/>rity after their departure from the '
              <lb/>haven. </p>
            <p> In this determination they quitted <lb/>the chamber, hand in hand through <lb/>the
              meadows, while invention sup- <lb break="no"/>plied the place of conversation until
              <lb/>they wandered down on the banks of <lb/><placeName>the Delaware</placeName> some
              miles; when on <lb/>some occasion <persName>Pulchera</persName> being a <seg
                xml:id="a008" corresp="#n008">few <cb/>
                <lb/>rods</seg><note xml:id="n008" corresp="#a008"><term style="font-style: italic"
                  >Rod</term>: a unit of measurement equal to 16.5 feet.</note> behind
                <persName>Constantius</persName> when just <lb/>entering a short turn of the bank,
              was <lb/><seg xml:id="a009" corresp="#n009">seized by half a dozen armed
                men,</seg><note xml:id="n009" corresp="#a009"><persName>Constantius</persName> is
                seized by a British impressment gang (or press gang). The Royal Navy established the
                practice of impressment in <date when="1664">1664</date> (and deployed it until
                  <date when="1814">1814</date>) to replace deserting sailors. Substandard wages
                made desertion commonplace, and by impressing “volunteers” into service the Royal
                Navy made sure that their ships had sufficient crews. The practice was a
                considerable source of friction between the <placeName>United States</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Great Britain</placeName> in the first decade of the nineteenth
                century, and was one of the nominal causes of the War of <date when="1812"
                  >1812</date>.</note>
              <lb/>who hurried him on board of a <seg xml:id="a010" corresp="#n010">boat.</seg><note
                xml:id="n010" corresp="#a010">In the original, this sentence reads “when on some
                occasion <persName>Pulchera</persName> being a few rods behind
                  <persName>Constantius</persName> when just entering a short turn of the bank, was
                seized by half a dozen armed men, who hurried her on board of a boat.” We have
                corrected the pronoun to conform to the details that follow.</note>
              <lb/><persName>Pulchera</persName>, who by the means of the <lb/>feeble rays of light
              which were retain- <lb break="no"/>ed by the atmosphere, had a dim <lb/>prospect of
              this transaction; and al- <lb break="no"/>though what she esteemed as her <lb/><seg
                xml:id="a011" corresp="#n011"><term style="font-style: italic">summum
                bonum</term>,</seg><note xml:id="n011" corresp="#a011"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Summum bonum</term>: the highest good (Latin).</note>
              was torn from her, <lb/>yet so sudden was the onset, and so <lb/>complete the
              surprize, that it sum- <lb break="no"/>moned all the tender and fearful feel- <lb
                break="no"/>ings which female nature is <choice><sic>susceptable</sic><corr>suscept-
                    <lb break="no"/>ible</corr></choice> of; and <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              retired behind <lb/>the opposite declivity of the bank, out <lb/>of the prospect of
              the scene, and se- <lb break="no"/>cure from their view. Dreadful <lb/>were the
              sensations which she here <lb/>experienced; her apprehensions of <lb/>personal danger
              being at last in some <lb/>measure abated, the safety of <persName>Con- <lb break="no"
                />stantius</persName> in the next instance occupied <lb/>her distracted bosom; she
              burst into <lb/>a flood of tears, and exclaimed, <lb/>“Oh! heavens, where is he! what
              <lb/>have they done with him! he is gone! <lb/>he is gone! never more shall my
              <lb/>wretched eyes behold him! he has <lb/>fallen a prey to relentless <emph
                style="font­-style: italic">British <lb/>barbarity</emph>! he must expire in some
              <lb/>loathsome prisonship, or give up the <lb/>ghost in some forlorn, death-impreg-
                <lb break="no"/>nated dungeon, without a friendly <lb/>hand to close his eyes when
              they are <lb/><choice><sic>dimed</sic><corr>dimmed</corr></choice> by death! why did
              my cow- <lb break="no"/>ardly fears prevail on me to leave <lb/>him? why did I not
              like a true lover <lb/>(as I thought I was) press forward <lb/>to him and have been a
              partner in his <lb/>misfortunes? had I been worthy the <lb/>name of a lover I should
              have done <lb/>it; but I was a stranger to love though <lb/>I professed it, and now I
              am justly <lb/>left to suffer torments greater than <lb/>would be probable on any
              circum- <lb break="no"/>stances where he was present. But <lb/>can I not yet get to
              him?—she <lb/>ran to the bank of the river where <lb/>she was seized by the party, but
              noth- <lb break="no"/>ing of him or his captors could be <lb/>discovered—Frantic in
              despair <lb/>she beat her breast, tore her hair, <lb/>cursed her fate and prayed for
              anni- <lb break="no"/>hilation, and was just about com- <pb/>
              <lb break="no"/>mitting her body to the watry grave, <lb/>when she was prevented
              therefrom, <lb/>by her father’s taking hold of her <lb/>arm. </p>
            <p> The consternation she was now in, <lb/>was more easily conjectured than de- <lb
                break="no"/>scribed.——Her father, unacquaint- <lb break="no"/>ed with what had
              happened to <persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName>, any further, than he
              gather- <lb break="no"/>ed from the exclamations of <persName>Pulchera</persName>,
              <lb/>suffered her to stay there no longer, <lb/>but instantly conducted her home, and
              <lb/>confined her to an inner chamber, <lb/>leaving her to the reflections of her
              <lb/>own mind, where sleep and comfort <lb/>were equally strangers to <seg
                xml:id="a012" corresp="#n012">her.</seg><note xml:id="n012" corresp="#a012">The
                second (<date when="1789-07">July</date>) installment ends here with the notice
                  “[<hi rend="italic">To be continued</hi>.]”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.03">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p> THE next day her father enter- <lb break="no"/>ed the
              chamber in a pleasant <lb/>air, inquiring her health, and saying <lb/>a variety of
              very agreeable things to <lb/>her—taking no notice of her late <lb/>elopement—At
              length, in soft ac- <lb break="no"/>cents, he observed to her that this <lb/>was the
              day on which <persName>M. <hi rend="italic">Le Monte</hi></persName>
              <lb/>had proposed to embark with her <lb/>for his native country, in order to
              <lb/>make her his wife; and that all he <lb/>waited for was to be informed of her
              <lb/>readiness to attend him. Her father <lb/>was about to proceed, but was inter- <lb
                break="no"/>rupted by <persName>Pulchera</persName>, who thus accost- <lb break="no"
              />ed him, ‘Dear father, the obligati- <lb break="no"/>on of paternal authority, and
              the <lb/>duty of filial obedience, are amongst <lb/>the first ideas which took place
              in <lb/>my mind; and with such forcible <lb/>lessons have those duties been incul- <lb
                break="no"/>cated on my mind, that nothing will <lb/>ever be able to deface them;
              and I <lb/>shall make it my first business as long <lb/>as I retain a rational
              existence, to <lb/>practice the one, and submit cheer- <lb break="no"/>fully to the
              other: But, dear and <lb/>respected father, the barely naming <lb/>of <persName>M. Le
                Monte</persName> to me, under <lb/>my circumstances, cannot fail of giv- <lb
                break="no"/>ing me sensations worse than the <lb/>most studied torture of <seg
                xml:id="a013" corresp="#n013"><emph style="font­-style: italic">Wheel</emph>
                <choice><sic>or</sic><corr>and</corr></choice>
                <lb/><emph style="font­-style: italic">Rack</emph>:</seg><note xml:id="n013"
                corresp="#a013"><term style="font-style: italic">Wheel and Rack</term>: medieval
                torture devices designed to cause prolonged suffering by slowly tearing a victim’s
                limbs from his or her torso.</note> But was I at my own dispo- <lb break="no"/>sal,
              you, Sir, could command no- <lb break="no"/>thing which I could hesitate at obey- <lb
                break="no"/>ing; but I am not my own—At <lb/>your special leave and request I have
              <lb/>in a most solemn manner given up <lb/>myself to <persName>Constantius</persName>,
              and am no <lb/>more my own—he took full possessi- <lb break="no"/>on of my heart when
              I gave him my <lb/>promise, and I have neither power <lb/>or inclination to take it
              back. You, <lb/>Sir, was present, and ratified our <lb/>contract by your most explicit
              ap- <lb break="no"/>probation thereof; and therefore <lb/>cease to possess the right
              or power <lb/>of disposing of me again: Pray, <lb/>dear Sir, give these considerations
              <lb/>that weight which they deserve—Re- <lb break="no"/>member that I am under the
              most <pb/>
              <lb/>solemn obligations to my dear <persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName>,
              that heaven has recognized <lb/>it, and that a violation thereof would <lb/>involve me
              in the horrid sin of per- <lb break="no"/>jury, which would eventually de- <lb
                break="no"/>prive me of every species of peace <lb/>here, and procure endless misery
              to <lb/>me hereafter. Consider also, I pray <lb/>Sir, that <persName>Le
                Monte</persName> is as odious <lb/>to me as <persName>Constantius</persName> is
              agreeable— <lb/>that his temper and disposition are <lb/>naturally fierce and cruel to
              the last <lb/>degree—that it is one of the articles <lb/>of his religion, that ‘no
              faith is to <lb/>be kept with hereticks,’ and such, <lb/>you are sensible, he esteems
              me— <lb/>that he despiseth that holy religion, <lb/>whose principles, in my early
              infan- <lb break="no"/>cy, you have taught me to have the <lb/>highest regard for, as
              being insepa- <lb break="no"/>rably connected with my <seg xml:id="a014"
                corresp="#n014">future wel- <lb break="no"/>fare</seg><note xml:id="n014"
                corresp="#a014"><persName>Pulchera’s</persName> family is Protestant, and
                  <persName>Le Monte</persName> is a Catholic; <persName>Pulchera</persName> argues
                that this difference makes them fundamentally incompatible.</note>—I hope you will
              reflect suita- <lb break="no"/>bly on these things, and not let the <lb/>idea of the
              pomp and show of tin- <lb break="no"/>sel’d greatness, and the place near a
              <lb/>Monarch’s court, induce you to de- <lb break="no"/>stroy the present peace and
              future <lb/>welfare of your only child.’ </p>
            <p> Her father listened to what she <lb/>said until she had gone through; <lb/>when,
              with a stern aspect, he reply- <lb break="no"/>ed, ‘Poor silly creature, your folly
              <lb/>would be your utter ruin, had you <lb/>not a father living to bridle your gid-
                <lb break="no"/>dy passions: But to reason with a <lb/>person void of rationality is
              no part <lb/>of my business. Remember you are <lb/>under my government, and that my
              <lb/>will is your law—that nothing will <lb/>be able to divert me from my pur- <lb
                break="no"/>pose of having <persName>Le Monte</persName> for a son- <lb/>in-law, and
              you may as well submit <lb/>to my pleasure quietly as to be drag- <lb break="no"/>ged
              to it by force, which will be the <lb/>case if you prove refractory. As to <lb/>your
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, he is a man whose <lb/>fortune does not exceed
              that to which <lb/>you are born; but <persName>Le Monte</persName> has an
              <lb/>inexhaustible fund both of riches <lb/>and honour.’ Thus saying, he left <lb/>her
              to her own doleful reflections. <lb/>Sleepless and wearisome moments <lb/>were her
              companions until the next <lb/>morning, when a servant of the fa- <lb break="no"/>mily
              entered the room, informing her <pb/>
              <lb/>it was her father’s pleasure that she <lb/>should prepare herself to breakfast
              <lb/>with <persName>Le Monte</persName> and himself; at <lb/>which he left the room,
              throwing <lb/>into her lap a news-paper of that <lb/>day. She took up the paper, and
              the <lb/>first thing she espied therein was the <lb/>fatal intelligence that
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, <lb/>after he had been taken prisoner by <lb/>the
              British, proved to be frantickly re- <lb break="no"/>fractory, that in a fit of rage
              one of <lb/>the officers had sheathed his sword in <lb/>his heart, and he was dead!—At
              the <lb/>reading of which, poor <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>swooned away and fell on the floor; <lb/>The noise of which brought the ser- <lb
                break="no"/>vant again into the apartment, for <lb/>by his master’s order he had
              waited <lb/>at the door to observe her—He, see- <lb break="no"/>ing her in that
              condition, called up <lb/>the family, and a long time it was <lb/>before they could
              restore her to her <lb/>senses; and when at last it was ef- <lb break="no"/>fected,
              with eyes starting with hor- <lb break="no"/>ror, she exclaimed, ‘He is gone! <lb/>He
              is gone! <persName>Constantius</persName> is no more! <lb/>Had it not been for my
              cruel father, <lb/>he would still have been alive with <lb/>me; but untimely death
              hath closed <lb/>his eyes; and you, Oh! my father, <lb/>must be answerable for that
              and all <lb/>its consequences! But you shall be <lb/>disappointed; never will I be
                <persName>Le <lb/>Monte’s</persName>. If I am deprived of him <lb/>in life, I will
              still be his in death— <lb/>He has had my heart, and I will ne- <lb break="no"/>ver
              give it to another; I will de- <lb break="no"/>scend to the grave; I will retire
              <lb/>from the theatre of this world, which <lb/>has no longer any thing in it to al-
                <lb break="no"/>lure me, and will seek that peace in <lb/>the unexplored regions of
              futurity, <lb/>of which I am deprived here by a <lb/>relentless father.’ </p>
            <p> To no purpose did her father at- <lb break="no"/>tempt to reason with her, telling
              her, <lb/>that as <persName>Constantius</persName> was dead she <lb/>was absolved from
              all her obligations <lb/>—that she, in consequence thereof, <lb/>was again under
              parental disposal— <lb/>that now she had no excuse of duty <lb/>to
                <persName>Constantius</persName>—that <emph style="font­-style: italic">that</emph>
              religion <lb/>which she the day before spoke so <lb/>highly of, made it her duty now
              to <lb/>submit to the dictates of her father, <pb/>
              <lb/>and that if she refused she must lose <lb/>his blessing and her own peace of
              <lb/>conscience here, and be sure of the <lb/>indignation of her Maker and Judge
              <lb/>hereafter; and that for her to conti- <lb break="no"/>nue obstinate would be of
              no service <lb/>to her, as she was totally in his pow- <lb break="no"/>er, and that he
              was fully determined <lb/>she should, that very night approach- <lb break="no"/>ing,
              embark with <persName>Le Monte</persName>.—She <lb/>observed to him, that to urge the
              <lb/>death of <persName>Constantius</persName> as an argument <lb/>for her again
              coming under his dis- <lb break="no"/>posal, when at the same time he was <lb/>in
              reality the guilty cause of it, did <lb/>not carry any great matter of force <lb/>with
              it, and that it was enough for <lb/>him to deprive her of
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, <lb/>without adding a curse of little less
              <lb/>magnitude to her misfortune; for <lb/>the joining her to <persName>Le
                Monte</persName> would <lb/>add as much to her wretchedness as <lb/>the depriving
              her of <persName>Constantius</persName>. </p>
            <p> Her father, finding that expostu- <lb break="no"/>lation had no kind of effect upon
              <lb/>her, withdrew; making preparation <lb/>for her embarkation; and the even- <lb
                break="no"/>ing following forced her into a coach <lb/>which conveyed her in the
              course of <lb/>the night to the wharf where lay the <lb/>ship in which <persName>Le
                Monte</persName> was to re- <lb break="no"/>turn to <placeName>France</placeName>,
              waiting for her arri- <lb break="no"/>val. She was hurried on board— <lb/>and the wind
              being favourable, they <lb/>hoisted sail, and in a few hours lost <lb/>sight of the
              American shore.—Grief, <lb/>amazement and horror occupied the <lb/>breast of
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, though <persName>Le Monte</persName>
              <lb/>used every effort to recommend him- <lb break="no"/>self to her; but all to no
              purpose. <lb/>She replied to him, that it was in <lb/>vain for him to attempt what was
              to- <lb break="no"/>tally impossible—that her aversion <lb/>to him was so great that
              time and <lb/>circumstances would never be able to <lb/>efface it—that tho’ he had the
              pow- <lb break="no"/>er over her body, yet her mind was, <lb/>and should continue
              free—that she <lb/>never would give him her hand or <lb/>heart, and that he might rest
              assured <lb/>he would never have the satisfaction <lb/>of being her husband—that even
              the <lb/>crown of <placeName>France</placeName> was too trifling a <lb/>toy to have
              any effect on her mind. <lb/>In discourses like this they passed a <cb/>
              <lb/>tedious passage of thirty-one days, <lb/>when one morning the light present- <lb
                break="no"/>ed to their view three British ships <lb/>at not more than half a
              league’s dis- <lb break="no"/>tance, at the leeward of them—A <lb/>flight was
              impossible—and in a few <lb/>minutes the nearest of the British <lb/>ships fired a
              shot across their bow. <lb/>The Captain of the French ship call- <lb break="no"/>ed
              his officers together and held a <lb/>momentary council of war, the re- <lb break="no"
              />sult of which was to strike their co- <lb break="no"/>lours and yield themselves
              prisoners <lb/>of war, which was done immediate- <lb break="no"/>ly. The Captain and
              some of his <lb/>principal officers, together with <persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName>
              and <persName>Pulchera</persName>, were carried <lb/>on board the Commandant’s ship;
              <lb/>but what was the surprise of <persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"/>ra</persName>,
              when on board of the captor she <lb/>beheld her lost <persName>Constantius</persName>!
              Nor <lb/>were the sensations of <persName>Constantius</persName>
              <lb/>less nervous at beholding his adora- <lb break="no"/>ble
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>—They both stood si- <lb break="no"/>lent, swallowed up
              in extacy, while <lb/>their expressive countenances decla- <lb break="no"/>red the
              emotions of their hearts more <lb/>intelligibly than the most finished
              <lb/>composition of words is capable of <lb/>doing. </p>
            <p> The Captain of the British ship, <lb/>on observing what passed, took <persName>Pul-
                  <lb break="no"/>chera</persName> into his cabin, saying, ‘Fair <lb/>lady, by the
              silent messages which <lb/>have passed between you and <persName>Con- <lb break="no"
                />stantius</persName>, a prisoner in my ship, I fan- <lb break="no"/>cy you have had
              some former ac- <lb break="no"/>quaintance with him, and that by <lb/>some means he
              has been forced from <lb/>you, and your meeting appears to be <lb/>unexpected to both;
              be so good as to <lb/>inform me of the circumstances, as <lb/>far as may be proper—You
              are both <lb/>in my power; I will see you have <lb/>ample justice done you.
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>then went on to inform him that she <lb/>was the only daughter of a rich far- <lb
                break="no"/>mer in the neighbourhood of <placeName>Phila- <lb break="no"
                />delphia</placeName>, that her father had paid ev- <lb break="no"/>ery attention to
              her education, that <lb/>at the age of seventeen her father in- <lb break="no"/>formed
              her that for three years past <lb/>he had made it the whole of his stu- <lb break="no"
              />dy to devise means of recommending <lb/>her to the only son of a wealthy <pb/>
              <lb/>merchant in the same neighbourhood, <lb/>whose name he said was
                <persName>Constantius</persName>; <lb/>and that <persName>Constantius</persName> and
              his father <lb/>had both agreed to the match, and <lb/>that he hoped there would be no
              ob- <lb break="no"/>jections thereto on her part—that <lb/>with blushes she told her
              father she <lb/>had no objection to offer to such a <lb/>proposal—that she had long
              had a <lb/>strong prepossession in favour of <persName>Con- <lb break="no"
                />stantius</persName>; in fine, she proceeded to <lb/>give him a brief history of
              the trans- <lb break="no"/>actions which we have before rela- <lb break="no"/>ted,
              until the then present moment. </p>
            <p> The Captain at the end of the <lb/>narration called <persName>Constantius</persName>
              into the <lb/>cabin, saying to him, ‘You have hi- <lb break="no"/>therto been a
              prisoner in my ship— <lb/>you from this moment cease to be <lb/>one—you are henceforth
              at liberty, <lb/>and have the freedom of the ship; <lb/>I congratulate you on your
              fortunate <lb/>meeting with your admired <persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"
                />ra</persName>—an elegant state-room shall be <lb/>allotted for your use—you and
                <persName>Pul- <lb break="no"/>chera</persName> shall henceforth participate <lb/>at
              my table, and when we arrive at <lb/><seg xml:id="a015" corresp="#n015"
                  ><placeName>Portsmouth</placeName>,</seg><note xml:id="n015" corresp="#a015"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><placeName>Portsmouth</placeName></term>: an island
                city off the southwest coast of <placeName>London</placeName> and an important naval
                port for the British in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</note> I will take
              suitable care <lb/>of you. You shall have a safe con- <lb break="no"/>veyance to <seg
                xml:id="a016" corresp="#n016"><placeName>Holland</placeName>,</seg><note
                xml:id="n016" corresp="#a016"><term style="font-style: italic"
                    ><placeName>Holland</placeName></term>: a neutral site during the Revolutionary
                War.</note> from whence at <lb/>your leisure you may return to your <lb/>native
                country.’—<persName>Constantius</persName> po- <lb break="no"/>litely returned him
              his warmest thanks <lb/>for his offered goodness, and nothing <lb/>but harmony
              subsisted in the cabin. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Le Monte</persName>, who continued a pri- <lb break="no"/>soner on board the
              same ship, in a <lb/>few days was informed of all that <lb/>had taken place with
              regard to <persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName> and
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, and was stung <lb/>with resentment at the
              information, <lb/>and swore revenge. The next day <lb/>he sent
                <persName>Constantius</persName> a challenge to a <lb/>duel, which he accepted; and
              that <lb/>night met for the purpose; in the <lb/>issue of which <persName>Le
                Monte</persName> fell, and <lb/>had to ask his life of
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, <lb/>who magnanimously gave it to <seg
                xml:id="a017" corresp="#n017">him.</seg><note xml:id="n017" corresp="#a017">Here the
                third (<date when="1789-08">August</date>) installment ends with the notice “(<hi
                  rend="italic">To be Continued.</hi>)”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.04">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p>
              <persName>LE MONTE</persName> was so sensible of <lb/>his obligation to
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, <lb/>that he rose and expressed his warm- <lb
                break="no"/>est acknowledgments to him on the <lb/>occasion; adding, that after
              experi- <lb break="no"/>encing such a favour from him, he <lb/>had too much gratitude
              to do any <lb/>thing which could in any degree prove <lb/>disagreeable to him:—I
              therefore, <lb/>said he, do relinquish every idea of <lb/>any claim to the admirable
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>—I resign her to you, Sir—Your <lb/>conduct has rendered you worthy of <lb/>her
              who has not an equal on earth— <lb/>May you long live mutual blessings <lb/>to each
              other, and may a beneficent <lb/>Providence grant that you may for- <lb break="no"
              />ever be sharers of the best of bless- <lb break="no"/>ings which heaven has reserved
              in <lb/>store for its dearest favourites; and <lb/>may I hope, that notwithstanding
              all <lb/>which has passed, that <persName>Le Monte</persName> will <lb/>be recorded
              amongst the number of <lb/>your friends. </p>
            <p> Nothing could exceed the courte- <lb break="no"/>sy with which
                <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Pul- <lb break="no"/>chera</persName>
              treated <persName>Le Monte</persName> on this occa- <lb break="no"/>sion; and the
              remainder of the voyage <lb/>was spent in the most agreeable man- <lb break="no"/>ner,
              until one night, after a most <lb/>beautifully serene day, they saw a
              <lb/>prodigiously black cloud make its ap- <lb break="no"/>pearance in the western
              hemisphere, <lb/>which was so hurried on by a terrific <lb/>gale, that in twenty
              minutes time it <lb/>totally obscured the whole face of <lb/>the heavens, and involved
              them in <lb/>one solid mass of substantial dark- <lb break="no"/>ness, while the wind
              continued to <lb/>rage with the wild madness of the <lb/>most violent hurricane, so
              that the <lb/>greatest skill and exertions of the of- <lb break="no"/>ficers and
              mariners became necessary <lb/>to prevent their being totally ingulph- <lb break="no"
              />ed in the bottom of the great deep. <lb/>What added to their frightful and
              <lb/>horrid situation was, that after it had <lb/>continued without any mitigation for
              <lb/>the space of about two hours, their <lb/>ears were saluted with the sound of <cb/>
              <lb/>distant thunder, which every moment <lb/>with astonishing rapidity, brought
              <lb/>nearer and nearer to their astonished <lb/>observation, until their ship, by the
              <lb/>flashes of lightning, seemed to be <lb/>wrapped in sheets of fire, which were
              <lb/>accompanied by such dreadful peals <lb/>of thunder as indicated that the final
              <lb/>dissolution of universal nature was <lb/>fast approaching, while torrents of
              <lb/>rain, as though the flood-gates of <lb/>heaven were unstopped, fell upon
              <lb/>them with such impetuousity as was <lb/>sufficient (one would have thought)
              <lb/>to have overwhelmed them in inevi- <lb break="no"/>table destruction. </p>
            <p> While in this pitiable situation, be- <lb break="no"/>ing the sport of the enraged
              elements, <lb/>at one moment tossed up to the clouds, <lb/>at the next immerged into
              the bot- <lb break="no"/>tom of the convulsed deep—expect- <lb break="no"/>ing every
              moment to be the last— <lb/>when nothing but fruitless cries and <lb/>lamentations
              were to be heard be- <lb break="no"/>tween those amazing peals of thun- <lb break="no"
              />der which kept almost constantly <lb/>bursting over their devoted heads, in <lb/>the
              tenth hour of this desperate con- <lb break="no"/>dition, they felt the shock of the
              <lb/>vessel’s striking on a bar—This was <lb/>but a completion of their despair—
              <lb/>the Captain, however, ordered the <lb/>long-boat to be thrown out, that any
              <lb/>who chose it might take their chance <lb/>in it, as it was more than probable
              <lb/>that the next sea would beat the ship <lb/>to pieces, and bury those in the sand
              <lb/>who remained on board; neither was <lb/>the prospect of venturing in the boat
              <lb/>any more favourable, as it was bor- <lb break="no"/>dering hard on impossible for
              a boat <lb/>to stand it for two minutes. It was <lb/>at this time
                <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"/>ra</persName>
              (who till then had kept hold of <lb/>each other’s hands) by some means <lb/>separated;
              and in a few minutes <persName>Pul- <lb break="no"/>chera</persName> discovered,
              through the medi- <lb break="no"/>um of the lightning, that she was the <lb/>only
              person remaining on board. <lb/>This circumstance, distressing as it <lb/>was, could
              add but little to her <lb/>wretchedness, which before was com- <lb break="no"
              />plete—She stood still, and resigned <lb/>herself to fate. It was not long be- <lb
                break="no"/>fore she perceived that the beating of <pb/>
              <lb/>the seas had made a fatal inroad on <lb/>the ship, which threatened every mo- <lb
                break="no"/>ment to come to pieces—which in <lb/>about five or six hours took place.
                <lb/><persName>Pulchera</persName>, who was almost in a sus- <lb break="no"/>pension
              of thought, found herself <lb/>floating on one of the hatches, on <lb/>which she was
              soon washed upon the <lb/>beach.—The disconsolate <persName>Pulchera</persName>,
              <lb/>with the small remains of strength <lb/>she yet possessed, was just able to
              <lb/>avoid the fury of the succeeding wave, <lb/>which if she had not escaped, could
              <lb/>not have failed of proving fatal to <lb/>her.—When she found herself be- <lb
                break="no"/>yond the reach of the boisterous sur- <lb break="no"/>ges, she reclined
              herself against the <lb/><choice><sic>declevity</sic><corr>declivity</corr></choice>
              of a bank, where she sat to <lb/>bemoan her disasterous fate—weari- <lb break="no"
              />ness overcame her, and she fell into <lb/>a sleep. When she awoke, she found
              <lb/>the storm had subsided, the boister- <lb break="no"/>ous wind had sunk into a
              perfect <lb/>calm, the sky was clear, the air was <lb/>serene, the face of nature
              appeared <lb/>smiling, the birds on the boughs fill- <lb break="no"/>ed the air with
              their melody, the sun <lb/>shone with peculiar lustre, and eve- <lb break="no"/>ry
              appearance seemed calculated to <lb/>inspire the bosom with pleasing sen- <lb
                break="no"/>sations; but all these circumstances <lb/>had no delights for
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>—a fixed <lb/>gloom occupied her countenance, <lb/>and
              the most melancholy sensations <lb/>rent her distressed breast; she wan- <lb
                break="no"/>dered, making an useless moan to <lb/>the heedless flowers which
              decorated <lb/>the wanton soil over which she ram- <lb break="no"/>bled.—Hours after
              hours in successi- <lb break="no"/>on passed away, while she traversed <lb/>the shore,
              where lay in forlorn ruins <lb/>the shattered remains of the ship; <lb/>but no signs
              of any of the people, <lb/>dead or alive, were to be found. </p>
            <p> In unsuccessful researches she spent <lb/>the day, in the course of which she
              <lb/>found she was on a small island, <lb/>which, though under cultivation, was
              <lb/>destitute of inhabitants. The night <lb/>succeeded the day, which she spent
              <lb/>in a manner not less joyless than the <lb/>day had been—But on the return of
              <lb/>day, just after bright <persName>Phœbus</persName> had ri- <lb break="no"/>sen
              from his orient bed, she disco- <lb break="no"/>vered a vessel coming down from the <cb/>
              <lb/>northward—As good fortune would <lb/>have it, she came within call of the
              <lb/>shore; she therefore, with a voice <lb/>as loud as her enfeebled situation
              <lb/>would admit, hailed them; and be- <lb break="no"/>ing asked what she desired? she
              an- <lb break="no"/>swered, that she was the only survi- <lb break="no"/>vor from a
              ship lately cast away there <lb/>in a storm, and wished to come on <lb/>board. The
              Captain ordered his <lb/>boat to bring her on board his ves- <lb break="no"/>sel,
              which was done accordingly.— <lb/>This vessel proved to be an American <lb/><seg
                xml:id="a018" corresp="#n018">privateer,</seg><note xml:id="n018" corresp="#a018"
                  ><term style="font-style: italic">Privateer</term>: A state-sponsored pirate.
                During the age of sail, privateers were privately owned armed vessels commissioned
                by governments to disrupt commercial shipping and seize their enemy’s merchant
                vessels.</note> fitted out from a port in <lb/><placeName>France</placeName>, the
                <persName>Captain being M—</persName>, <lb/>of <placeName>New York</placeName>, with
              whom <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>had formerly had a slight acquaint- <lb break="no"/>ance, and knowing him to be a
              gen- <lb break="no"/>tleman of strict honour, she informed <lb/>him of the whole of
              her adventure. <lb/><persName>Capt. M.</persName> was very much affected with <lb/>her
              story, but with no part of it more <lb/>than with the hapless fate of his friend
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName>, with whom he had been <lb/>bred at school,
              and for whom he en- <lb break="no"/>tertained the greatest regard: and <lb/>nothing in
                <persName>Captain M’s</persName> power was <lb/>left unessayed to render
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>happy: and she experienced every <lb/>mark of distinction, as well from all
              <lb/>the officers as the Captain and sea <lb/>men, which their situation would ad- <lb
                break="no"/>mit of. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Captain M.</persName> informed her that af- <lb break="no"/>ter a few days’
              cruise in those parts, <lb/>they were bound to <placeName>America</placeName>, and
              <lb/>on their arrival there it should be <lb/>some of his first business to see her
              <lb/>conducted safely to her friends; and <lb/>in a few days they sat out to put
              <lb/>this purpose in effect—Nothing ma- <lb break="no"/>terial happened the first ten
              days— <lb/>but on the eleventh day, they found <lb/>they were chased by a vessel of
              supe- <lb break="no"/>rior force, and that she gained con- <lb break="no"/>siderably
              upon them—and it was soon <lb/>made certain that she was a vessel of <lb/>more than
              twice their force, conse- <lb break="no"/>quently a capture (extraordinaries
              <lb/>excepted) was unavoidable. <persName>Capt. <lb/>M.</persName> advised
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, in order to es- <lb break="no"/>cape any ill usage
              from their captors, <lb/>to divest herself of women’s appa- <lb break="no"/>rel, and
              attire herself in a suit of his, <lb/>which she accordingly did, putting <pb/>
              <lb/>on a neat suit of red regimentals, a <lb/>gold-laced hat, and a sword by her
              <lb/>side, and took upon her the charac- <lb break="no"/>ter of a Lieutenant, under
              the name <lb/>of <persName>VALORUS</persName>.—By this time their <lb/>pursuer was
              within reach of them, <lb/>which was announced by the discharge <lb/>of one of her bow
              guns. <persName>Capt. M.</persName>
              <lb/>on a more particular inspection of <lb/>his enemy, began to conceive some
              <lb/>hope of being able to make good his <lb/>defence against them: he according- <lb
                break="no"/>ly made ready for an action, which soon <lb/>commenced with great fury
              on both <lb/>sides. In a few moments the com- <lb break="no"/>batants were at not more
              than sixty <lb/>feet distance, while an incessant dis- <lb break="no"/>charge of
              cannon, many of which <lb/>were loaded with <seg xml:id="a019" corresp="#n019"
                >langrage</seg><note xml:id="n019" corresp="#a019"><term style="font-style: italic"
                  >Langre</term>: A type of canon shot consisting of scrap iron packed into a case;
                often used in naval warfare to damage sails and rigging.</note> and <seg
                xml:id="a020" corresp="#n020">grape- <lb/>shot,</seg><note xml:id="n020"
                corresp="#a020"><term style="font-style: italic">Grape-shot</term>: A type of canon
                shot consisting of small round balls packed into a canvas sack (thus said to
                resemble a cluster of grapes).</note> was sufficient to have effectual- <lb
                break="no"/>ly tried the fortitude of the oldest ve- <lb break="no"/>terans; and for
              a very considerable <lb/>time fortune seemed undetermined <lb/>in whose favour to
              decide, until a <lb/>well directed fire from the British <lb/>caused <persName>Capt.
                M.</persName> to strike his colours, <lb/>and thereby decided the action.— <lb/>The
              captor put a <seg xml:id="a021" corresp="#n021">prize-master on <lb/>board of the
                prize,</seg><note xml:id="n021" corresp="#a021"><term style="font-style: italic"
                  >Prize-master</term>: a naval officer put in charge of a seized ship. <term
                  style="font-style: italic">Prize</term>: a naval term for an enemy ship seized in
                battle and destined to be sold as the spoils of war. Prize ships made privateering
                profitable.</note> taking the offi- <lb break="no"/>cers (amongst whom was
                <persName>Valorus</persName>, <lb/>under the character of a lieutenant) <lb/>into
              his own vessel. </p>
            <p> The captor proved to be a sloop <lb/>of war from <placeName>Portsmouth</placeName>,
              bound to <lb/><seg xml:id="a022" corresp="#n022"
                ><placeName>Quebec</placeName>.</seg><note xml:id="n022" corresp="#a022"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><placeName>Quebec</placeName></term>: formerly the seat
                of power for <placeName>New France</placeName>, the city had been ceded to the
                British at the conclusion of the Seven Years War in <date when="1763">1763</date>.
                By the 1770s, <placeName>Quebec</placeName> had become the center of British
                authority in <placeName>Canada</placeName>. The city was also the site of the first
                major defeat of the Continental Army in late <date when="1775-12">December of
                  1775</date>.</note>
              <persName>Captain M.</persName> and his officers <lb/>received as good treatment on
              board <lb/>the sloop as could reasonably be ex- <lb break="no"/>pected from the hands
              of a captor; <lb/>in particular the delicate appearance <lb/>of
                <persName>Valorus</persName> insured to him an un- <lb break="no"/>common degree of
              respect from the <lb/>under officers and men—she kept her <lb/>countenance as smooth
              as the unruf- <lb break="no"/>fled sea, though at the same time her <lb/>recollection
              of <persName>Constantius</persName> totally <lb/>destroyed every agreeable idea which
              <lb/>was about to rise in her mind, tho’ <lb/>none but her pillow was a witness to
              <lb/>her immoderate grief on the occa- <lb break="no"/>sion. </p>
            <p> They pursued their voyage for <lb/><placeName>Quebec</placeName>, where the
              prisoners had the <lb/>promise of being liberated, they giv- <lb break="no"/>ing their
              parole not to enter into ac- <lb break="no"/>tual service against the British until <cb/>
              <lb/>regularly exchanged: but how fickle <lb/>is fortune! When they supposed, by
              <lb/>their reckoning, they were near in <lb/>with the land, a terrible storm assail-
                <lb break="no"/>ed them, which continued without <lb/>intermission day after day,
              the wind <lb/>rather increasing than diminishing, <lb/>till on the night of the third
              day af- <lb break="no"/>ter the commencement of the storm; <lb/>when, about one
              o’clock, they were <lb/>alarmed by the breaking of the sea
                  <lb/><choice><sic>But</sic><corr>but</corr></choice> a very small distance a-head
              of <lb/>them, a sure indication that a bar, <lb/>shoal, rocks, or land, was there, and
              <lb/>so nigh was it, that all attempts to <lb/>avoid it were made use of in vain—
              <lb/>they had scarcely time to realize their <lb/>situation before their vessel was a-
                <lb break="no"/>ground—Their fate was apparently <lb/>fixed, and their small remains
              of <lb/>hope seemed to be totally annihilated. <lb/>But this suspense lasted not long;
              <lb/>the wind was so violent and the seas <lb/>so enormous, that the fourth sea af-
                <lb break="no"/>ter the first struck reduced her to a <lb/>heap of ruins; and the
              hands, by <lb/>the violence of the waves, were wash- <lb break="no"/>ed on the shore,
              which was but a <lb/>few feet distant from the bow of the <lb/>vessel, and they had
              the surprising <lb/>good fortune to escape a watery tomb, <lb/>saving three only, who
              were drown- <lb break="no"/>ed.—They endeavoured to seek a <lb/>shelter from the storm
              by advancing <lb/>up on the land; but all attempts of <lb/>this nature were in vain,
              for, twenty <lb/>feet from the water was the farthest <lb/>they could extend, by
              reason of a <lb/>bank which ascended nearly perpen- <lb break="no"/>dicular; and the
              state of the night <lb/>was so dark that they could form no <lb/>idea of its height;
              and as they tra- <lb break="no"/>versed to the right hand and the left, <lb/>they
              found it was not to be avoided <lb/>either way, as at a short distance it <lb/>butted
              down on the water; and they <lb/>found they must content themselves <lb/>in that
              situation until morning: But <lb/>they were overwhelmed by one very <lb/>melancholy
              consideration, <term style="font-style: italic">viz</term>. That <lb/>they were
              totally ignorant of what <lb/>time in the tide it was; if it should <lb/>happen to be
              any thing near low-wa- <lb break="no"/>ter, they could not possibly avoid be- <lb
                break="no"/>ing swallowed up long before it was <pb/>
              <lb/>high-water: However, it so happen- <lb break="no"/>ed that at the time of their
              being <lb/>cast ashore it was about high-water, <lb/>and by keeping a constant
              observation <lb/>they soon found that the tide was on <lb/>the ebb, which eased them
              from their <lb/>dismal apprehensions on that account. <lb/>The night, however, passed
              away in <lb/>a very joyless manner.—When the <lb/>day-light appeared, the storm still
              <lb/>continuing, no very pleasing pros- <lb break="no"/>pect presented itself to their
              view— <lb/>The beach on which they were, was <lb/>about thirty rods in length, bounded
              <lb/>by an unsurmountable ledge of rocks <lb/>to the height of 150 feet, which but-
                <lb break="no"/>ted at each extremity into the sea, <lb/>the ends of which they in
              vain at- <lb break="no"/>tempted <seg xml:id="a023" corresp="#n023">to
                double;</seg><note xml:id="n023" corresp="#a023"><term style="font-style: italic"
                  >Double</term>: a naval term for sailing around a cape or point of land.</note>
              their boats they <lb/>found crushed in ruins with the re- <lb break="no"/>mains of
              their ship.—Providentially, <lb/>amongst the rubbish they found con- <lb break="no"
              />siderable quantities of provisions; but <lb/>unfortunately, no kind of tools lar-
                <lb break="no"/>ger than a jack-knife could they ob- <lb break="no"/>tain, though
              the most diligent search- <lb break="no"/>es were made therefor.—They bu- <lb
                break="no"/>sied themselves in securing their pro- <lb break="no"/>vision, by
              carrying it above the reach <lb/>of the tide. They then secured a few <lb/>barrels of
              ammunition which they <lb/>found undamaged, and some fire- <lb break="no"/>arms.
              Fruitless attempts were then <lb/>made to ascend the precipice, until <lb/>experience
              had taught them that no- <lb break="no"/>thing was to be expected from their <lb/>most
              vigorous <seg xml:id="a024" corresp="#n024">exertions.</seg><note xml:id="n024"
                corresp="#a024">The fourth (<date when="1789-09">September</date>) installment ends
                here with the note “(<hi rend="italic">To be continued.</hi>)”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.05">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p> HAVING secured the whole of <lb/>the provisions they could
              find <lb/>among the ruinous remains of their <lb/>ship, they began to collect
              materials <lb/>for building a raft, and immediately <lb/>began to erect one, though
              this <lb/>business went on very slowly for the <lb/>want of tools proper to execute it
              <lb/>with, however, they did as well as <lb/>they could, and in the course of <lb/>two
              or three days by their exertions, <pb/>
              <lb/>they had fabricated sufficient to float <lb/>the whole of the unhappy sufferers,
              <lb/>on board of which the next morning <lb/>they embarked with a part of their
              <lb/>provisions, their fire arms, and a <lb/>quantity of ammunition; with this
              <lb/>they pushed off from the shore, the <lb/>weather being very cold, and the
              <lb/>heavens indicated the approach of a <lb/>storm. </p>
            <p> It was a question at first, which <lb/>way they should direct their
                  course<choice><sic>,</sic><corr>.</corr></choice>
              <lb/>At last it was agreed to cruise along <lb/>shore, to the eastward. They pros- <lb
                break="no"/>ecuted this intention, at about three, <lb/>and sometimes four rods
              distance <lb/>from the shore, for five or six miles, <lb/>while nothing appeared to
              them to <lb/>favour their wishes—nothing but a <lb/>perpendicular ledge of ragged
              rocks <lb/>was to be seen; and by this time <lb/>the snow began gently to descend.
              <lb/>They kept a constant look out for a <lb/>place where it was possible for them
              <lb/>to run their raft ashore, where they <lb/>might encamp on dry land; but <lb/>this
              they long sought in vain, till to- <lb break="no"/>wards evening, when the snow had
              <lb/>fallen to the depth of twelve or thir- <lb break="no"/>teen inches, they
              discovered a small <lb/>declivity in the bank, where they <lb/>ran their raft on
              shore. And through <lb/>this declivity they ascended the <lb/>bank, which was about
              one hundred <lb/>feet in length. When they had at- <lb break="no"/>tained the summit,
              they had an ex- <lb break="no"/>tensive uncultivated plain in <seg xml:id="a025"
                corresp="#n025">pursuit,</seg><note xml:id="n025" corresp="#a025"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Pursuit</term>: in front of them.</note>
              <lb/>and not the least sign that any thing <lb/>human was ever there before them.
              <lb/>With some difficulty in collecting <lb/>materials, they built them a comfort- <lb
                break="no"/>able fire, and frying a quantity of <lb/>bread and meat, they soon eat a
              <lb/>very hearty supper; by this time <lb/>it being dark, they made prepara- <lb
                break="no"/>tions for <choice><sic>takeing</sic><corr>taking</corr></choice> some
              repose. In the <lb/>morning they awoke and beheld a <lb/>serene air, and a pleasant
              sky—they <lb/>consulted what course they should <lb/>then take, when it was agreed
                  <choice><orig>to</orig><reg>that they should</reg></choice> di- <lb break="no"
              />vide into a number of small com- <lb break="no"/>panies, each company to take a dif-
                <lb break="no"/>ferent route, taking a quantity of <lb/>provisions each, and if
              either party <lb/>found any inhabitants, to return to <cb/>
              <lb/>that place and wait for the return <lb/>of the rest.
              <persName>VALORUS</persName>, with two others, <lb/>composed one of those small com-
                <lb break="no"/>panies, each taking a gun, a quanti- <lb break="no"/>ty of
              ammunition and provisions, <lb/>they each took their different route, <lb/>the snow
              being about six inches <lb/>deep. The first day they spent in <lb/>exploring the
              inhospitable wilder- <lb break="no"/>ness, without meeting with any thing <lb/>worthy
              of remark. On the latter <lb/>part of the second day they were <lb/>overtaken by a
              furious storm of snow, <lb/>they travelled till almost night, and <lb/>seeing no kind
              of probability of find- <lb break="no"/>ing any inhabitants, they concluded <lb/>to
              stop under the <seg xml:id="a026" corresp="#n026"
                    ><choice><sic>lee-wrad</sic><corr>lee-ward</corr></choice></seg><note
                xml:id="n026" corresp="#a026"><term style="font-style: italic">Lee-ward</term>:
                nautical term for the side away from the wind.</note> side of a <lb/>large rock, and
              make as good prepa- <lb break="no"/>rations for the insuing night as they <lb/>could,
              which was only to tread down <lb/>the snow, and collect such fuel as <lb/>they could,
              to support a fire. The <lb/>storm continued to rage with uncom- <lb break="no"/>mon
              fury during the whole of the <lb/>night and the succeeding day, dur- <lb break="no"
              />ing which time, it was with the <lb/>greatest difficulty they kept them- <lb
                break="no"/>selves from freezing, their fuel be- <lb break="no"/>ing exhausted, and
              it was with the <lb/>greatest difficulty that they procured <lb/>a small quantity
              more. They found <lb/>on the abatement of the snow, that <lb/>it had fallen between
              four or five <lb/>feet in depth, and by reason of its <lb/>not being capable of
              sustaining half <lb/>the weight of a man, it was intirely <lb/>out of their power to
              proceed, either <lb/>backward or forward. </p>
            <p> In this situation, all they could <lb/>do, was to make themselves as com- <lb
                break="no"/>fortable as they could where they <lb/>were; the weather was so
              intencely <lb/>cold, that a large fire was indispen- <lb break="no"/>sibly necessary,
              and though they <lb/>were surrounded with timber, they <lb/>lacked the means of
              falling it; how- <lb break="no"/>ever they collected the small remains <lb/>of wood
              which they had, and after <lb/>incredible pains, they beat a track <lb/>to an old
              large dry oak tree, at about <lb/>a rod’s distance from them, and <lb/>kindled a fire
              in a fracture at the <lb/>bottom thereof, by which means in <lb/>less than two hours
              they burned <lb/>down, which providentially falling <pb/>
              <lb/>across the rock, broke and split the <lb/>main trunk to pieces; this was a
              <lb/>very valuable acquisition, making as <lb/>much as <seg xml:id="a027"
                corresp="#n027">two cords and an half of <lb/>wood.</seg><note xml:id="n027"
                corresp="#a027"><term style="font-style: italic">Cord</term>: a measure of cut wood,
                especially wood used for fuel. The term most likely derives from the practice of
                using a cord of rope to insure that stacks were of equivalent dimensions (typically
                a cord was a stack 4 feet wide by 4 feet long and 8 feet high).</note> This lasted
              them for better <lb/>than three days, when their situation <lb/>seemed to arrive to
              the height <lb/>of wretchedness, the rigor of the <lb/>weather not having in any
              degree <lb/>abated, and their small store of pro- <lb break="no"/>visions they had
              brought with them <lb/>being entirely spent, there seemed <lb/>nothing but inevitable
              death before <lb/>their eyes, for although a second <lb/>similar attempt had furnished
              them <lb/>with a very considerable stock of <lb/>wood, yet with nothing else to sus-
                <lb break="no"/>tain nature, death could not appear <lb/>at a very great distance
              from them, <lb/>especially as their natural strength <lb/>by excessive exertions, the
              inclemen- <lb break="no"/>cy of the weather, severe hardships, <lb/>and want of food
              was greatly ex- <lb break="no"/>hausted. </p>
            <p> In this situation they lived or <lb/>rather existed for six days, having <lb/>no
              kind of sustenance, excepting the <lb/>bark of trees which as it was frozen, <lb/>they
              could get off only in very small <lb/>pieces with their knives, and then <lb/>thawing
              by the fire, chewed and <lb/>swallowed it. </p>
            <p> At the commencement of the se- <lb break="no"/>venth day, when their sufferings had
              <lb/>reduced them to a surprising state of <lb/>weakness, and it was become certain
              <lb/>that they could subsist but a very little <lb/>time longer, they began to <seg
                xml:id="a028" corresp="#n028">wreck</seg><note xml:id="n028" corresp="#a028"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Wreck</term>: probably a misspelling of “rack,” as in
                the expression “to rack one’s brains.”</note>
              <lb/>their invention to determine what <lb/>they should do next; in vain did <lb/>they
              then lament that they had not, <lb/>as soon as the storm abated have at- <lb
                break="no"/>tempted to have forced a way thro’ <lb/>the snow back to their
              rendezvous, <lb/>though the prospect was very un- <lb break="no"/>promising, it being
              according to the <lb/>best of their judgment, nearly fifty <lb/>miles; but it was now
              too late to <lb/>think of an attempt like that; and <lb/>after mutually condoling each
              other <lb/>on their desperate situation, one of <lb/>the party thus addressed his
              partners, <lb/><term style="font-style: italic">Dear fellow sufferers</term>. In our
              sad <lb/>situation, a few hours more will <cb/>
              <lb/>close our eyes, to be opened no <lb/>more; we now cease to be any ad- <lb
                break="no"/>vantage to each other; and though <lb/>life is hard to part with, yet it
              is of <lb/>little consequence to either of us, <lb/>whether we die this day or to-mor-
                <lb break="no"/>row; and if <emph style="font­-style: italic">one</emph> dying to
              day will <lb/>eventually save the life of the <emph style="font­-style: italic">two
                <lb/>survivors</emph>, one had much better die <lb/>alone for the other two to live,
              than <lb/>for all three to die together. For <lb/>my part as one, I move that we cast
              <lb/>lots which of us shall die, to save the <lb/>other two.—If it falls to my lot, I
              <lb/>will submit to my fate without a <lb/>murmur.—Nay, I had rather die
              <lb/>instantly, than to die this lingering- <lb break="no"/>ly with my two suffering
              partners. <lb/>The other two seemed well pleased <lb/>with the proposal; the lots were
              <lb/>immediately prepared, and it was <lb/>the fate of <persName>Valorus</persName> to
              be the victim. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Valorus</persName> told them if they would <lb/>indulge him so far as to
              give him <lb/>time to write but a few lines to his <lb/>father, which he wished them
              to take <lb/>the care of, and if ever an opportu- <lb break="no"/>nity presented, that
              they would for- <lb break="no"/>ward to him, and that then he would <lb/>willingly
              resign to his fate—they <lb/>granted his request, and he wrote <lb/>as follows: </p>
          </div> <div type="letter">
            <floatingText>       <body>         
                        <opener><salute><choice><sic>DRAR</sic><corr>DEAR</corr></choice>
                    PAPPA,</salute></opener>
                <p> FROM the centre of a frozen <lb/>wilderness on the borders of <lb/>the grave,
                  please to receive this last <lb/>token from your only child—driven <lb/>from home,
                  I have been the sport of <lb/>fortune, but fifteen minutes will put <lb/>me out of
                  her power. I shall then <lb/>be in a state of changeless retribution. <lb/>Had I
                  not been obliged, by a fa- <lb break="no"/>ther’s stern command, to forego a
                  <lb/>promise I made by his express li- <lb break="no"/>cence, I might still have
                  lived and <lb/>have been happy—as far as I am
                      <lb/>concerned<choice><sic>.</sic><corr>,</corr></choice> I forgive you
                  heartily, <lb/>but pray Sir, see that you are pre- <lb break="no"/>pared to stand
                  at the bar of the <choice><sic>Omnicient</sic><corr>Omni- <lb break="no"
                      />scient</corr></choice> Judge. </p>
                <head style="text-align:right"><seg xml:id="a029" corresp="#n029"><closer><signed>
                        <name role="pseudonym" type="person">YOUR LOST
                      CHILD</name>.</signed></closer></seg><note xml:id="n029" corresp="#a029">Here
                    the fifth (<date when="1789-10">October</date>) installment ends with the note,
                      “(<hi rend="italic">To be continued.</hi>)”</note></head>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.06">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p>
              <persName>VALORUS</persName> had just finished <lb/>the letter, and delivered it,
              <lb/>when one of his woeful partners took <lb/>up the fatal gun, well loaded, and
              <lb/>had got it to his face, and was just <lb/>pulling the trigger in order to lodge <cb/>
              <lb/>its contents in his head, when he <lb/>chanced to raise his eyes a little, and
              <lb/>discovered a Bear wallowing in the <lb/>snow, at about 20 yards distance— <lb/>He
              exclaimed, “<persName>Valorus</persName>! thank <lb/>God you may yet live!” and dis-
                <lb break="no"/>charged his piece at the Bear, lodg- <lb break="no"/>ing two balls
              in his head, of which <lb/>he died instantly.—If ever joy was <lb/>to excess, it was
              then so amongst <lb/>this little unfortunate company—<persName><emph
                  style="font­-style: italic">Valorus</emph></persName>
              <lb/>whom they both loved equal to <lb/>themselves, was still alive—without <lb/>going
              to their prey, they both fell <lb/>upon him, embracing him as one <lb/>from the dead,
              and the most tender, <lb/>expressive congratulations passed on <lb/>the occasion—they
              all seemed lost <lb/>in extacy for some space of time. </p>
            <p> After their effusions of joy were <lb/>in some measure abated, their small
              <lb/>remains of strength were exerted in <lb/>beating a road to their new acquired
              <lb/>provision, which after having with <lb/>difficulty proceeded, they made a
              <lb/>small repast upon. By this time it <lb/>was night, and the Heavens had
              <lb/>gathered an unusual degree of black- <lb break="no"/>ness, and very soon a
              torrent of rain <lb/>began to descend.—They so fixed <lb/>their bear-skin (which was a
              very <lb/>large one) as to be a very consider- <lb break="no"/>able shelter to them
              from the rain, <lb/>and kept them tolerably dry thro’ <lb/>the sleepless night.—The
              light of <lb/>day at last approached, after the most <lb/>rainy night they had ever
              known, <lb/>when soon the clouds broke away, <lb/>the wind sprung up at North-West,
              <lb/>and a very severe cold day ensued. <lb/>So much water was in the snow, and
              <lb/>the cold so severe, that by the mid- <lb break="no"/>dle of the day it was froze
              suffi- <lb break="no"/>ciently to bear them, which they <lb/>perceiving, formed an
              idea of trying <lb/>to regain their place, of general <lb/>rendezvous; but their
              enfeebled <lb/>state was such, that they scarcely <lb/>were determined whether to
              attempt <lb/>it or not; but after mature delib- <lb break="no"/>eration it was
              concluded to set out <lb/>in the morning, which accordingly <lb/>they put in practice,
              taking with <lb/>them a quantity of meat, which they <pb/>
              <lb/>judged sufficient for their use, till <lb/>such time as they should arrive at
              <lb/>their place of rendezvous. </p>
            <p> It is needless to recount the weari- <lb break="no"/>some steps which they
              experienced <lb/>on their journey; suffice it to say, <lb/>that on the fifth day, just
              before <lb/>night, they arrived at the place ex- <lb break="no"/>ceedingly fatigued,
              which they found <lb/>in the same situation they had left it, <lb/>and no
                  <choice><sic>sign</sic><corr>signs</corr></choice> were to be discovered <lb/>that
              any person having been there since <lb/>their departure; but it was so near <lb/>the
              windward side of the land, that <lb/>the wind in the time of the falling <lb/>of the
              snow, had driven the snow <lb/>quite off from that place.—Fatigued <lb/>as they were,
              they built a fire, and <lb/>provided some supper:—Here they <lb/>found bread, pork,
              beef, tea, sugar, <lb/>and some cooking utensils, which <lb/>they had left there; and
              they pre- <lb break="no"/>pared and eat a more comfortable <lb/>meal than they had
              since their being <lb/>cast away. The next day they had <lb/>recourse to their raft,
              which they <lb/>found inclosed with ice;—they then <lb/>repaired on the ice to the
              place of <lb/>their shipwreck, which they likewise <lb/>found the snow drifted off
              from. <lb/>Tired of any further researches, they <lb/>consulted which was the best
              place <lb/>to fix their abode at, and when they <lb/>had considered that at this place
              was <lb/>the greater part of the provisions they <lb/>had to depend on—that here, from
              <lb/>the ruins of their ship, were materials <lb/>for building them a shelter—and that
              <lb/>likewise, here they could draw fuel <lb/>from the same resource. They una- <lb
                break="no"/>nimously agreed to make that the <lb/>place of their residence, hoping
              they <lb/>had provisions enough to carry them <lb/>through the winter, and that in the
              <lb/>spring Providence would find some <lb/>way for their deliverance. Under <lb/>the
              impression of these ideas they went <lb/>to work, and fabricated themselves <lb/>a
              hut, tolerably warm;—and, to <lb/>add to their good fortune, amongst <lb/>the ruins of
              the ship they found <lb/>a cask of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> rum, and another
              <lb/>of brandy, and about <seg xml:id="a030" corresp="#n030">£. 8900</seg><note
                xml:id="n030" corresp="#a030">£: in the 1780s, this number of British pounds would
                be roughly equivalent to <placeName>US</placeName> $900,000 today.</note> in
              <lb/>cash, tho’ <emph style="font­-style: italic">that</emph> they looked on as a <cb/>
              <lb/>very small acquisition, but they se- <lb break="no"/>cured it:—In this situation
              they <lb/><choice><orig>esteemed</orig><reg>considered</reg></choice> themselves
              tolerably happy; <lb/>but a misfortune now attacked them <lb/>which they were in no
              measure pre- <lb break="no"/>pared for. <persName>Valorus</persName>, and one of his
              <lb/>companions were taken sick of a <seg xml:id="a031" corresp="#n031"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Plu- <lb break="no"/>risy</term>;</seg><note
                xml:id="n031" corresp="#a031"><term style="font-style: italic">Pleurisy</term>: a
                viral infection of the lungs. In addition to shortness of breath, other accompanying
                symptoms include harsh coughing, diarrhea, fever, chills, and chest pains.</note>
              this deadly disorder seized them <lb/>so violently that in three days both of
              <lb/>their lives were despaired of by them- <lb break="no"/>selves and their
              companion, who left <lb/>nothing unattempted, which he had <lb/>reason to hope would
              contribute to <lb/>their recovery. There was nothing <lb/>but what the unfortunate two
              un- <lb break="no"/>derwent, both from the extreme ra- <lb break="no"/>ging of their
              distemper, and also from <lb/>the forlorn situation which they were <lb/>unfortunately
              in; however, contrary <lb/>to their own, and their companion’s <lb/>expectations, on
              the <choice><sic>eight</sic><corr>eighth</corr></choice> day their <lb/>fever broke,
              and by slow degrees they <lb/>regained their wonted strength, so <lb/>that in about
              five weeks they were <lb/>able to walk about, and were in a <lb/>good measure, able to
              do such kind <lb/>of business as their circumstances re- <lb break="no"/>quired to be
              done.—They now spent <lb/>their time as agreeably as could be <lb/>expected for people
              in such lonely <lb/>circumstances, saving only the discon- <lb break="no"/>solate
                <persName>Valorus</persName>, who as her thoughts <lb/>began to be less taken up on
              her own <lb/>personal safety, the idea of her belov- <lb break="no"/>ed
                <persName>Constantius</persName> would keep continual- <lb break="no"/>ly arising in
              her distracted mind. The <lb/>horrors of that dreadful night where- <lb break="no"/>in
              they parted by shipwreck, to meet <lb/>no more, would keep continually <lb/>harrowing
              up her mind, and depriv- <lb break="no"/>ing her of every species of comfort— <lb/>her
              mind was distracted with terrific <lb/>dreams, and her days spent in melan- <lb
                break="no"/>choly reflections. At times she was <lb/>half resolved to unbosom
              herself to <lb/>her <choice><sic>comrads</sic><corr>comrades</corr></choice>; but
              reasons of policy <lb/>forbid the measure:—They still un- <lb break="no"/>suspecting
              but <persName>Valorus</persName> was really <lb/>what he appeared to be—a man. </p>
            <p> In this situation they spent their <lb/>time, until the return of spring, at
              <lb/>which time their provision was nearly <lb/><seg xml:id="a032" corresp="#n032"
                >exhausted;</seg><note xml:id="n032" corresp="#a032">Here the <date when="1789-11"
                  >November</date> installment ends—in mid-sentence!—with the note “(<hi
                  rend="italic">To be continued.</hi>)”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.07">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p> WHEN one morning, to their <lb/>inexpressable satisfaction,
              <lb/>they espied a small vessel, not more <lb/>than a league and an half from
              <lb/>shore. They made use of every <lb/>means in their power, to give them <lb/>notice
              of their situation, by firing <lb/>guns of distress, which at last had <lb/>the
              desired effect, and the vessel stood <lb/>in for the shore, till they got within
              <lb/>call, when they hailed them, and asked <lb/>what they wished? They gave them
              <lb/>a short account of their disaster, and <lb/>that in all probability they were the
              <lb/>only survivors of a large crew. The <lb/>vessel sent their boat ashore and took
              <lb/>them on board. She proved to be <lb/>a privateer from a port of <placeName>Essex
                <lb/>county</placeName>, in <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> state.— <lb/><emph
                style="font­-style: italic"><persName>Valorus</persName></emph> did not think proper
              to <lb/>make known her sex, tho’ she in- <lb break="no"/>formed them he was an
              American, <lb/>and that he was a prisoner when he <lb/>had the misfortune to be
              shipwrecked. <lb/>The Captain of the privateer, told
              <lb/><persName>Valorus</persName>if he would enter on board <lb/>voluntarily, he
              should be intitled out <lb/>of the dead shares to a Lieutenent’s <lb/>proportion of
              the prize money, the <lb/>hands on board having agreed there- <lb break="no"/>to,
                <persName>Valorus</persName> accepted thereof— <lb/>as for the other two, it was
              <lb/>agreed they should be sat at liberty <lb/>the first
                  <choice><sic>opportuuity</sic><corr>opportunity</corr></choice> which pre- <lb
                break="no"/>sented. </p>
            <pb/>
            <p> They cruised on this coast about <lb/>a week, when they fell in with, and <lb/>took
              a brigantine from <seg xml:id="a033" corresp="#n033"
                ><placeName>Bristol</placeName></seg><note xml:id="n033" corresp="#a033"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><placeName>Bristol</placeName></term>: an important
                eighteenth-century British commercial port, crucial in the triangular trade.</note>
              bound <lb/>to <placeName>Quebec</placeName>, with a valuable cargo on <lb/>board. The
              captain of the privateer <lb/>put <persName>Valorus</persName> on board as prize-mas-
                <lb break="no"/>ter, with a sufficiency of hands, and <lb/>ordered her into <seg
                xml:id="a034" corresp="#n034"><placeName>Salem</placeName>;</seg><note xml:id="n034"
                corresp="#a034"><term style="font-style: italic"
                ><placeName>Salem</placeName></term>: was the seventh largest city in the
                  <placeName>U.S.</placeName> in <date when="1790">1790</date> and a primary port
                for American privateers during the Revolutionary War.</note> but unfor- <lb
                break="no"/>tunately the next day she was captur- <lb break="no"/>ed by a British
              cruiser, and was carried <lb/>into <seg xml:id="a035" corresp="#n035"
                  ><placeName>Halifax</placeName>.</seg><note xml:id="n035" corresp="#a035"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><placeName>Halifax</placeName></term>: a city in
                  <placeName>Nova Scotia</placeName> and the site of the largest British naval base
                on the <placeName>Atlantic coast</placeName> during the late eighteenth century.
                During the Revolutionary War, the city was also a haven for loyalists who fled north
                to <placeName>British Canada</placeName>.</note>
              <persName>Valorus</persName> had, thro’ <lb/>his unacquaintedness with this kind
              <lb/>of business, left the papers which he <lb/>had of the captain of the privateer,
              <lb/>on board of her; and when the capt. <lb/>demanded his papers, he had no- <lb
                break="no"/>thing to shew. In vain did <persName>Valorus</persName>
              <lb/>inform him of the whole of the trans- <lb break="no"/>action. The captain of the
              cruiser <lb/>said any one might make as good a <lb/>story as that—he accordingly put
                <lb/><persName>Valorus</persName>in <emph style="font­-style: italic">irons</emph>,
              and when they ar- <lb break="no"/>rived at <placeName>Halifax</placeName>, (perceiving
              that <lb/>the irons hurted his wrists, they <lb/>were taken off) he was put into the
              <lb/>dungeon, and there kept in order for <lb/>a trial for <seg xml:id="a036"
                corresp="#n036"><emph style="font­-style: italic">piracy</emph>.</seg><note
                xml:id="n036" corresp="#a036">Prior to <date when="1778">1778</date>, the British
                did not legally recognize American soldiers as prisoners of war and thus subjected
                them to criminal prosecutions. While the chronology of events in the text is murky,
                the reference to Valorus’ forgotten papers likely means that it takes place after
                this date. In other words, he is treated as a pirate (and thus as a criminal) and
                not as a privateer (and thus as a prisoner of war), because he cannot prove that he
                was apprehended while acting in the service of a government commission.</note>
            </p>
            <p> Those who are acquainted <choice><orig>in</orig><reg>with</reg></choice>
              <placeName>Ha- <lb break="no"/>lifax</placeName> know that the <seg xml:id="a037"
                corresp="#n037">Provost,</seg><note xml:id="n037" corresp="#a037"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Provost</term>: the structure serving as the
                headquarters of the military police. In <date when="1777">1777</date>, the
                  <persName>Provost Marshall of <placeName>Halifax</placeName></persName> was
                suspended from duty because of the high number of prisoners who escaped from his
                jail. This episode likely alludes to the reputation of
                  <placeName>Halifax</placeName> prison as poorly secured.</note> under <lb/>which
              the dungeon is situated, stands <lb/>on a rising piece of ground, and <lb/>that from a
              vault in the bottom of <lb/>the dungeon, there is a drain of <lb/>about two feet
              square, which leads <lb/>from the said vault out to the side of <lb/>the hill on which
              the provost stands. <lb/>After <persName>Valorus</persName> had been confined in
              <lb/>this place about ten days (the ele- <lb break="no"/>venth being appointed for his
              trial) <lb/>he got acquainted with this circum- <lb break="no"/>stance of the drain,
              he therefore, in <lb/>company with some others, deter- <lb break="no"/>mined to make
              their escape through <lb/>that avenue: they therefore, one by <lb/>one, let themselves
              down into the <lb/>vault, and crept out through the <lb/>drain on their hands and
              knees, it <lb/>being about half filled up with filth; <lb/>however, they lived through
              the <lb/>operation, though it was nauseous to <lb/>the last degree, and they all got
              safe- <lb break="no"/>ly through, though they were all be- <lb break="no"/>daub’d in
              filth, in order to divest <lb/>themselves of it, they had imme- <lb break="no"/>diate
              recourse to the water, where <cb/>
              <lb/>they found a small <seg xml:id="a038" corresp="#n038">shallop,</seg><note
                xml:id="n038" corresp="#a038"><term style="font-style: italic">Shallop</term>: a
                large heavy boat fitted with at least one mast and sometimes furnished with
                guns.</note> on board <lb/>of which they entered, and under <lb/>cover of the night
              got clear of the <lb/>harbour: But their <seg xml:id="a039" corresp="#n039"><emph
                  style="font­-style: italic">evil genius</emph></seg><note xml:id="n039"
                corresp="#a039"><term style="font-style: italic">Evil genius</term>: the bad spirits
                following them.</note> had <lb/>not yet left them, for the second day <lb/>after
              their escape they were taken up <lb/>by a small vessel of force, bound from <lb/><seg
                xml:id="a040" corresp="#n040"><placeName>Penobscot</placeName></seg><note
                xml:id="n040" corresp="#a040"><term style="font-style: italic"
                    ><placeName>Penobscot</placeName></term>: a port city in what is now central
                  <placeName>Maine</placeName>. During the early stages of the Revolutionary War,
                  <placeName>Penobscot</placeName> was the site of a humiliating defeat for the
                Americans (the worst naval defeat in <placeName>U.S.</placeName> history until
                  <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName>). The American survivors who were not captured
                were forced to walk into <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> with little in the way
                of provisions or equipment.</note> to <placeName>London</placeName>; so their
              <lb/>pleasing hopes of seeing home was <lb/>once more brought to nothing. </p>
            <p> The captain of this little cutter, <lb/>proved to be a very good natured <lb/>sort
              of a man, and <persName>Valorus</persName> made it <lb/>his business to enter as far
              into his <lb/>good graces as possible, and he had <lb/>every success he could wish
              for, and <lb/>on their arrival at <placeName>London</placeName> he sat
                <lb/><persName>Valorus</persName>and the rest of the prisoners <lb/>at liberty. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Valorus</persName> now found the advantage <lb/>of the money which he had
              saved <lb/>out of the wreck, he having about <lb/>200 <seg xml:id="a041"
                corresp="#n041">guineas</seg><note xml:id="n041" corresp="#a041"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Guineas</term>: gold coins worth a British pound. The
                coins were named after the <placeName>Guinea region</placeName> in
                  <placeName>Africa</placeName> were the gold was originally mined. Two hundred
                guineas would be the modern day equivalent of about $US 30,000.</note> in his
              pockets which <lb/>his captors had not taken from him, <lb/>he procured himself a
              couple of <lb/>suits of genteel cloaths, and in a few <lb/>days had an opportunity to
              embark <lb/>for <placeName>Lisbon</placeName>, and from there in a few <lb/>days more
              for <seg xml:id="a042" corresp="#n042"><placeName>France</placeName>.</seg><note
                xml:id="n042" corresp="#a042"><persName>Valorus’s</persName> circuitous route from
                London to Lisbon to <placeName>France</placeName> demonstrates how hostilities
                between <placeName>England</placeName> and <placeName>France</placeName> made direct
                travel almost impossible.</note> When he <lb/>arrived at
                <placeName>France</placeName>, his first enqui- <lb break="no"/>ry was, if any
              Americans were in <lb/>that place or not. As it happened <lb/>there was present a
              French officer <lb/>who understood the English language <lb/>tolerably well, who
              informed him <lb/>that at the next door but one, there <lb/>lodged an American
              gentleman, who <lb/>he believed was of a very considerable <lb/>rank in the world. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Valorus</persName>
              <choice><sic>steped</sic><corr>stepped</corr></choice> to the door, and <lb/>asked if
              he could have lodgings there <lb/>till an opportunity presented for him <lb/>to ship
              for <emph style="font­-style: italic"><placeName>America</placeName></emph>? he was
              answer- <lb break="no"/>ed in the affirmative, and entering <lb/>the house, he was
              conducted into a <lb/>parlour, where saw a gentleman <lb/>reading a manuscript: the
              gentle- <lb break="no"/>man rose to receive him, but how <lb/>great was the
              astonishment of <persName>Valo- <lb break="no"/>rus</persName>, when in the face of
              the gentle- <lb break="no"/>man he recognized every feature of <lb/><emph
                style="font­-style: italic">the long (thought) lost</emph>
              <persName>CONSTANTIUS</persName>. <lb/>At first thought, <persName>Valorus</persName>
              had like to <lb/>have made a discovery of who he <lb/>was, by making the most
              pathetick <pb/>
              <lb/>acclamations; but a second thought <lb/>forbid any thing like that; knowing
              <lb/>that “<emph style="font­-style: italic">time and absence cures the fond- <lb
                  break="no"/>est love</emph>,” so taking each other by the <lb/>hand they passed
              mutual &amp; civil com- <lb break="no"/>pliments, and each took seats. <persName>Con-
                  <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName> ordered a bottle of wine and <lb/>some
              glasses, and after drinking <lb/>to each others health,
                <persName>Constantius</persName>
              <choice><sic>enquired</sic><corr>in- <lb break="no"/>quired</corr></choice> what part
              of <placeName>America</placeName>
              <persName>Valo- <lb break="no"/>rus</persName> was from? he informed him he
              <lb/>belonged to a privateer from <placeName>Salem</placeName>, <lb/>that he was
              captured and carried in- <lb break="no"/>to <placeName>Halifax</placeName>, from
              whence he made <lb/>his escape, was again taken, carried <lb/>into
                <placeName>England</placeName>, where he was libera- <lb break="no"/>ted, and had
              came to this place in <lb/>order to seek a passage home. Just <lb/>as this discourse
              happened, a French <lb/>gentleman entered the parlour, whom
                <lb/><persName>Valorus</persName>at first sight knew to be <emph
                style="font­-style: italic"><persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName></emph>, the first
              cause of all her trou- <lb break="no"/>ble; mutual compliments passed <lb/>between
                <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Constantius</persName>Le Monte,
              <lb/>and Miscellaneous discourse passed <lb/>away the time until supper was serv- <lb
                break="no"/>ed; <persName>Valorus</persName> then proposed taking <lb/>his lodging,
              and was conducted to <lb/>his bed: <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Le
                Monte</persName>
              <lb/>afterwards repaired to their lodging, <lb/>which was separated from that of
                <lb/><persName>Valorus</persName>only by a partition. </p>
            <p> Sleep had in a great measure de- <lb break="no"/>parted from
                <persName>Valorus</persName>—He attended <lb/>to the discourse of
                <persName>Constantius</persName> and <lb/><persName>Le Monte</persName> after they
              had taken their <lb/>beds. He found there was the most <lb/>intimate friendship
              subsisting be- <lb break="no"/>tween them, and that a purpose of <lb/>marriage was on
              foot between <persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName> and the only sister of
                <persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName>, and that she would be in <lb/>town on the morrow
              from <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <choice><sic>and and</sic><corr>
                  <lb/>and</corr></choice>that in a short time the nuptials <lb/>were to be
              celebrated. Confusion <lb/>now took full possession of the dis- <lb break="no"
              />tressed heart of <persName>Valorus</persName>. She view- <lb break="no"/>ed her
                <persName>Constantius</persName> as totally lost to <lb/>her forever; now did she
              curse her <lb/>unfortunate stars, and lamented the <lb/>time she escaped the gaping
              liquid <lb/>grave, and all the horrors of the dis- <lb break="no"/>consolate island on
              which she had <lb/>been shipwrecked; but most of all <lb/>the ill fated moments which
              again <cb/>
              <lb/>introduced her to the presence of <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName>.—Despair
              and anguish <lb/>rent her heart through the tedious <lb/>watches of the night, and her
              pillow <lb/>was wet with the choicest tears <lb/>that ever flowed within the realm of
                <lb/><placeName>France</placeName>. </p>
            <p> On the return of the morning they <lb/>all arose, and every preparation was
              <lb/>making for the reception of the lady,
                    <lb/><persName><choice><sic>Le.</sic><corr>Le</corr></choice>
              Monte’s</persName>sister. Breakfast was <LB/>at last brought on the table;
                <persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName>, <persName>Constantius</persName> and
                <persName>Valorus</persName>
              <lb/>sat down.—<persName>Valorus</persName> enquired of
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName> what part of <placeName>America</placeName>
              <lb/>he was from? he replied, from <placeName>Phi- <lb break="no"
                />ladelphia</placeName>.— Pray sir, said he, did you <lb/>ever have any acquaintance
              with a <lb/>gentleman by the name of ——? <lb/><emph style="font­-style: italic">(we
                must be excused for omitting his <lb/>name here.)</emph> Yes, replied
                <persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName>, with a very expressive counte-
                <lb break="no"/>nance.—Did you know a daughter <lb/>of his by the name of
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>? <lb/>Yes, replied <persName>Constantius</persName>,
              with a de- <lb break="no"/>gree of melancholy in his face,— <lb/>Why? continued
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, was <lb/>you ever acquainted with her? some
              <lb/>years ago, replied <persName>Valorus</persName>, I was <lb/>very intimate in the
              family, and if I <lb/>forget not, when I last knew the fa- <lb break="no"/>mily she
              was the only surviving child <lb/>which her father had. Can you in- <lb break="no"
              />form me if ever she married, or <lb/>whether she is yet alive or not? <lb/>This
              question brought tears into the <lb/>eyes of <persName>Constantius</persName>, who
              with a <lb/>voice which bespoke the perturbation <lb/>of his mind, replied—poor
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, <lb/>the ornament of her sex, and the <lb/>pride of
              human nature, is no more: <lb/>some misunderstanding with her fa- <lb break="no"/>ther
              with regard to a proposed mar- <lb break="no"/>riage, caused her to leave her home,
              <lb/>and to cross the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>, in which <lb/>voyage the vessel
              was wrecked, and <lb/><emph style="font­-style: italic">dear
                  <persName>Pulchera</persName></emph> was the only person <lb/>who was lost!—His
              tears prevented <lb/>him from proceeding any further, <lb/>and
                <persName>Valorus’s</persName> feelings were too sen- <lb break="no"/>sible to
              prosecute the enquiry. Af- <lb break="no"/>ter breakfast <persName>Valorus</persName>
              asked <persName>Con- <lb break="no"/>stantius</persName> to walk with him in the gar-
                <lb break="no"/>den. <persName>Constantius</persName> rather declined, <lb/>saying,
              he should be exceeding fond <pb/>
              <lb/>and proud of an interview, but it <lb/>was absolutely necessary for him to
              <lb/>make all the preparation he could to <lb/>receive some company of rank which
              <lb/>would attend on him in the after- <lb break="no"/>noon, in consequence of which,
              sir, <lb/>said he, I dare say you will excuse <lb/>me. <persName>Valorus</persName>
              replied, he had too <lb/>much good nature to urge him to a <lb/>measure that was
              disagreeable to him, <lb/>and retired to his chamber and wrote <lb/>a letter to
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, then walked <lb/>out to take a view of the town,
              giv- <lb break="no"/>ing the letter to a boy in the street, <lb/>making a present to
              him of a <lb/>guinea to secure the delivery of it to <lb/>the lady of the house where
                <persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName> boarded. In about half an hour
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName>received the letter of the <lb/>lady, he broke
              it open and read as <lb/>follows: </p>
          </div> <div type="letter">
            <floatingText>       <body><hi rend="italic">          <opener><salute>Dear
                        <persName>Constantius</persName>,</salute></opener>
                  <p> THOUGH through the adversity of <lb/>fickle fortune, I have for a long time
                    <lb/>been deprived of my only happiness, <lb/>which consisted in being with the
                    ami- <lb break="no"/>able <persName>Constantius</persName>, and though perhaps
                    <lb/>my name may by this time be obliterated <lb/>from your memory, yet yours is
                    not, <lb/>and never will cease to rest in mine; <lb/>and no satisfaction or
                    comfort shall I <lb/>enjoy, until we have an opportunity to <lb/>fulfil, those
                    sacred promises which we <lb/>have mutually made to each other. </p>
                  <head style="text-align:right"><closer>This from the comfortless <lb/><signed><hi
                          rend="roman"><persName>PULCHERA</persName></hi>.</signed></closer></head>
                </hi>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
          </div> <div type="section">      <p>
              <persName>Constantius</persName> was thunderstruck at <lb/>reading these lines,
              viewing the writ- <lb break="no"/>ing he would exclaim—“It must be <lb/>so—I am too
              well acquainted with <lb/>the hand to be capable of being im- <lb break="no"/>posed
              on.—She is still alive, and I <lb/>am her’s, and she is mine! an indis- <lb break="no"
              />soluble bond has united us together, <lb/>which nothing but death is capable <lb/>of
              dissolving. O heavens where is <lb/>she? I am on the <emph style="font­-style: italic"
                >rack</emph> till I behold <lb/>her! Where can she be? Where is <lb/>the post-boy
              who delivered the let- <lb break="no"/>ter? &amp;c. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Constantius</persName> went on in such like <lb/>exclamations until
                <persName>Le Monte</persName> came <lb/>in, to whom he read the letter. <persName>Le
                <lb/>Monte</persName> was a little struck at first <lb/>hearing it, but on
              considering the <cb/>
              <lb/>subject, he told Constantius it was <lb/>impossible for it to be a reality, but
              it <lb/>was a piece of imposition contrived <lb/>by some ill-minded person, in order
              <lb/>to break off his proposed marriage <lb/>with his sister; saying, you know,
              <lb/>you positively know, my <persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName>, that
              it is beyond the reach of <lb/>possibilities for her to be alive.—She <lb/>did not
              leave the ship with us, and it <lb/>is not in the power even of credu- <lb break="no"
              />lousness itself to form an idea of her <lb/>escaping.
                <persName>Constantius</persName> stood in a <lb/>maze; at last he replied, “it must
              <lb/>be, you are in the right, it is impossi- <lb break="no"/>ble she should be alive,
              she is long <lb/>since paid the great debt of nature, <lb/>and is no more.”
                <persName>VALORUS</persName> continued <lb/>to walk the streets, wishing to know
              <lb/>the effect which the letter had on the <lb/>mind of
                <persName>Constantius</persName>, not being able <lb/>to form a judgment of how his
              af- <lb break="no"/>fections stood towards <persName>Pulchera</persName>; <lb/>about
              noon he returns to the house, <lb/>closely examining the looks of <persName>Con- <lb
                  break="no"/>stantius</persName>, but could read nothing in his <lb/>countenance
              for certain.—He then <lb/>enters into a discourse with him, in <lb/>the course of
              which he enquires of <lb/>him how long since he was in <placeName>Phi- <lb break="no"
                />ladelphia</placeName>? he answered about six <lb/>or eight weeks.—Was the father
              of <lb/><persName>Pulchera</persName> alive when you left the <lb/>place? He was—Was
              he much af- <lb break="no"/>fected with the death of his daugh- <lb break="no"/>ter?
              exceedingly, it had like to have <lb/>ruined his senses. I think when I <lb/>was there
              last, continued <persName>Valorus</persName>, a <lb/>certain gentleman by the name of
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName>was paying his addresses <lb/>to
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>.—Do you know any <lb/>thing with regard to him?
                <persName>Constan- <lb break="no"/>tius</persName>, with some tender emotions,
              <lb/>replied, yes I am the person.—I was <lb/>once happy in the love of the most
              <lb/>amiable <persName>Pulchera</persName>; she engrossed the <lb/>whole of my soul,
              and I believe I had <lb/>no less share in the affections of
                <lb/><persName>Pulchera</persName> but cruel death, that in- <lb break="no"
              />terrupter of human felicity, forced <lb/>her from me, and left me inconsola- <lb
                break="no"/>bly to bemoan her hapless fate.— <lb/>Shipwrecked on the coast of
                <placeName>England</placeName>, <lb/>having but a moment to avail our- <lb
                break="no"/>selves of the boat (which was at best <pb/>
              <lb/>but a <emph style="font­-style: italic">forlorn hope</emph>) I by some means
              <lb/>let go her hand, and in the confusion <lb/>I did not perceive it ’till after I
              was <lb/>in the boat, and the <seg xml:id="a043" corresp="#n043">fast was cut from
                <lb/>the vessel.</seg><note xml:id="n043" corresp="#a043"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Fast</term>: the rope which lashes the longboat to the
                ship.</note> Distracted I had like to <lb/>have thrown myself from the boat
              <lb/>into the water and attempted to <lb/>have regained the vessel and mingled
              <lb/>fates with her; but being fully <lb/>sensible of the impracticability of
              <lb/>regaining the vessel, I contented <lb/>myself to live, expecting though <lb/>that
              every moment would be the <lb/>last, however we floated in a man- <lb break="no"/>ner
              really miraculous, about four <lb/>or five miles, when, providentially <lb/>we struck
              on a small uninhabited <lb/>island, two days after which we <lb/>were taken off by a
              pleasure boat, <lb/>who went with us to the island on <lb/>which we supposed our
              vessel was <lb/>wrecked, which proved to be the <lb/><seg xml:id="a044"
                corresp="#n044">same.</seg><note xml:id="n044" corresp="#a044">Here the <date
                  when="1789-12">December</date> installment ends with the note “(<hi rend="italic"
                  >To be concluded in our next.</hi>)”</note>
            </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>

    <group>
      <text corresp="#15579.08">   <body>
          <div type="section">      <p> HERE was I in hopes of finding <lb/>my
                <persName>Pulchera</persName> whether dead or <lb/>alive, but my hopes were in vain,
              not <lb/>a trace of her was to be found; a <lb/>small trunk of her’s I found wash’d
              <lb/>up, which I took into possession, out <lb/>of which I took this locket, having
              <lb/>her picture set in gold, this I have <lb/>ever worn on my breast, and <lb/>never
              shall it be transfered to any <lb/>other place—O thou amiable <persName>Pul- <lb
                  break="no"/>chera</persName>! never will your image be <lb/>erased from my
              memory—never shall <lb/>I forget the time when we exchang- <lb break="no"/>ed mutual
              vows, and gave ourselves <lb/>up to each other, when joys extatic <lb/>took full
              possession of our enraptured <lb/>breasts at anticipating scenes of feli- <lb
                break="no"/>city, which we fondly promised our- <lb break="no"/>selves, but which
              cruel fortune never <lb/>designed we should realize—here
                    <lb/><persName><choice><sic>Constantius</sic><corr>Constantius’s</corr></choice></persName>
              utterance failed him, here <lb/>he gave himself up to a flood of <lb/>immoderate
              grief, and <persName>Valorus</persName> could <lb/>scarcely contain himself—at length
              in <lb/>broken accents he thus accosted him, <lb/>“<emph style="font­-style: italic"
                >Dear Sir</emph>, I pray that you would <lb/>moderate your grief which can be
              <lb/>of no service to you—your sorrows <lb/>can never reanimate
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, when <lb/>death separates lovers, tho’ it is im- <lb
                break="no"/>possible intirely to forget, yet duty <lb/>makes it necessary to banish
              every <lb/>idea as far as is practicable—you <lb/>may no doubt find another to supply
              <lb/>the place of <persName>Pulchera</persName>.” O reply’d
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName>, these are the reflexions <lb/>of a mind at
              ease—’tis true I cannot <lb/>reanimate the admirable <persName>Pulchera</persName>—
              <lb/>she has bid a final farewell to all <seg xml:id="a045" corresp="#n045">sub- <lb
                  break="no"/>lunary</seg><note xml:id="n045" corresp="#a045"><term
                  style="font-style: italic">Sublunary</term>: of or belonging to this world,
                earthly, terrestrial.</note> things, but my veneration for <lb/>her will never cease
              to exist, neither <lb/><choice><sic>will</sic><corr>will it</corr></choice> in any
              degree abate.—’Tis true <lb/>I have sought relief in the arms of <lb/>another, and
              soon, very soon are the <lb/><choice><sic>nuptial</sic><corr>nuptials</corr></choice>,
              to be celebrated, but there <lb/>is nothing which can erase that su- <lb break="no"
              />preme affection which I have once for <lb/>all placed on the inimitable
                <persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"/>ra</persName>; she is no more! </p>
            <cb/>
            <p> Dear Sir, replyed <persName>Valorus</persName> your <lb/>affections were very
              sincere, and pro- <lb break="no"/>vidence will never admit of such vir- <lb break="no"
              />tues going unrewarded—It must <lb/>have in its store of beneficence some
              <lb/>peculiar blessing to bestow upon you, <lb/>and tho’ I am no prophet I will ven-
                <lb break="no"/>ture to predict that your days of sor- <lb break="no"/>row are
              nearly at an end—something <lb/>you have no idea of at present will <lb/>soon open
              upon you which will inspire <lb/>you with such sensations as you have <lb/>a long time
              been a stranger to—I <lb/>pray you to dismiss the subject, and <lb/>ask me no further
              questions on the <lb/>matter—whether ever you see me <lb/>again or not, remember what
              I now <lb/>say to you.—Saying this he bid him <lb/>adieu, and could not be prevailed
              on <lb/>to stay any longer with him—he <lb/>walked away into the City, leaving
                <lb/><persName>Constantius</persName> in amazement. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Constantius</persName> employ’d his reason- <lb break="no"/>ing powers to
              conclude what the se- <lb break="no"/>quel of this matter should be; vari- <lb
                break="no"/>ous were his conjectures ’tho he <lb/>could form
                  <choice><sic>do</sic><corr>no</corr></choice> fixed idea in his own <lb/>mind—he
              walked into the house, sat <lb/>down and continued his rumination <lb/>on this
              inexplicable adventure; <lb/>while he was musing came in a boy <lb/>and delivering him
              a letter retired— <lb/>he opened the letter and read, </p>
          </div> <div type="letter">
            <floatingText>       <body>“<hi rend="italic">          <opener><salute>Dear
                      Sir,</salute></opener>
                  <p> If you will call at the sign of the Eagle <lb/>at half past four precisely,
                    you will <lb/>hear of something you very little expect, <lb/>and which concerns
                    you in the highest <lb/>degree, after that it will be too late. </p>
                  <closer><head style="text-align:right; font-style:roman">ADIEU.”</head></closer>
                </hi>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
          </div> <div type="section">      <p> This still served to increase his <lb/>wonder—but he
              considered it rather <lb/>as an unfortunate appointment on <lb/>one account, as that
              was the time <lb/>appointed for the arrival of <persName>Le
                    <lb/><choice><sic>Mont’s</sic><corr>Monte’s</corr></choice></persName> sister,
              whom he wished to <lb/>receive with all the respect possible— <lb/>he at one time
              would imagine it was <lb/>a stratagem of some enemy of his, <lb/>in order to introduce
              a friend between <lb/>him and his proposed bride, and then <lb/>he would determine to
              pay no kind of <lb/>attention to the message, then again <lb/>the anxiety of his mind
              would be <lb/>such, that he resolved, let the event <pb/>
              <lb/>be what it would, he would attend <lb/>the summons—accordingly at a little
              <lb/>past four he made preparations to go, <lb/>and at twenty-five minutes sat out,
              <lb/>but as he had left the door, he look- <lb break="no"/>ed round and discovered his
              proposed <lb/>bride, approaching at some distance <lb/>attended with a very splendid
              retinue, <lb/>at the sight of which staggered his <lb/>resolution of proceeding—it
              could <lb/>not fail of striking his mind most <lb/>powerfully, that if he absented
              him- <lb break="no"/>self at this time, the lady would con- <lb break="no"/>ceive such
              a dislike at this want of <lb/>respect, that she would abandon him <lb/>forever, and
              that he should draw upon <lb/>him the revenge of <persName>Le Monte</persName>, and
              all <lb/>his connexions—however, his curio- <lb break="no"/>sity was so great, and his
              anxiety so <lb/>irresistible, that his determination to <lb/>go, overcame every
              consideration to <lb/>the contrary.—He therefore turned <lb/>his face towards the
              Eagle and suffer- <lb break="no"/>ed nothing to divert his steps—he <lb/>arrived at 29
              minutes past four, at <lb/>the door he met a <seg xml:id="a046" corresp="#n046"
                >barber, and a toilet <lb/>woman going out.</seg><note xml:id="n046" corresp="#a046"
                  ><term style="font-style: italic">Barber and toilet woman</term>: hairdresser and
                domestic servant who assisted in washing and dressing elite women.</note> He asked
              the <lb/>hostess if there were any commands <lb/>there for him? she answered, that in
              <lb/>the chamber parlour was a young <lb/>gentleman waiting for you, if your <lb/>name
              is <persName>Constantius</persName>, that is my name <lb/>replyed he—she shewed him
              the way <lb/>to the room, which he entered—but <lb/>heavens, what a surprize was he
              seiz- <lb break="no"/>ed with, when he instead of a young <lb/>gentleman, found his
              eyes fixed <lb/>on his adorable <persName>PULCHERA</persName>; decked <lb/>in all the
              magnificence which the <lb/>city of <seg xml:id="a047" corresp="#n047"
                  ><placeName>Bordeaux</placeName></seg><note xml:id="n047" corresp="#a047"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><placeName>Bordeaux</placeName></term>: an important
                port city in the southwest <placeName>France</placeName> and a central hub for trade
                between <placeName>France</placeName> and the <placeName>West
                Indies</placeName>.</note> could afford—she <lb/>rose in the most graceful manner
              <lb/>to receive him, such a sweetness was <lb/>in her countenance, as could not fail
              <lb/>of ravishing the heart of the most stu- <lb break="no"/>pid beholder, her eyes
              acquired ad- <lb break="no"/>ditional lustre, as they met those of <lb/>her long
              wished for <persName>Constantius</persName>, <lb/>whose surprise was so great, that
              his <lb/>organs of speech were totally incapa- <lb break="no"/>ble (for a while) to
              perform their <lb/>functions, while <emph style="font­-style: italic"
                  ><persName>Pulchera</persName></emph> thus ad- <lb break="no"/>dressed him: “<emph
                style="font­-style: italic">Dear <persName>Constantius</persName></emph>,
                  <choice><sic>It</sic><corr>it</corr></choice>
              <lb/>is long since my heart has been to- <lb break="no"/>tally in your possession, and
              many and <cb/>
              <lb/>great have been the sufferings which <lb/>I have passed through for the sake of
              <lb/>him whom I have now the pleasure <lb/>of beholding, and you Sir, and you
                <lb/><emph style="font­-style: italic">only</emph> know whether my sufferings have
              <lb/>been in vain or not—you Sir, <lb/>know whether I am to be happy in <lb/>your
              favour, or whether the sister of <lb/><persName>Le Monte</persName> predominates in
              your affec- <lb break="no"/>tions.—You Sir, can decide on a ques- <lb break="no"/>tion
              which is of more consequence <lb/>to me than the riches of both the <placeName>In- <lb
                  break="no"/>dies</placeName>.—My complete happiness, and <lb/>my insuperable
              misery, are now sus- <lb break="no"/>pended in the ballance of your mind, <lb/>and as
              the one or the other scale prepon- <lb break="no"/>derates, will my fate be happy or
              <lb/>miserable in the extreme—yet Sir, do <lb/>not misunderstand me, perhaps my
              <lb/>language conveys ideas different <lb/>from my intentions, notwithstanding
              <lb/>the many terms I have made use <lb/>of, I value your repose so
                  <choice><sic>higly</sic><corr>highly</corr></choice>, that <lb/>I never can wish
              you to do a thing <lb/>disagreeable to yourself, in order to <lb/>oblige me; and even
              an event like <lb/>that, was I sensible of it, would only <lb/>add to my torment—If
                  <choice><sic>Sir, </sic><corr>Sir, I</corr></choice> have poses- <lb break="no"
              />sion of your heart, I shall be thank- <lb break="no"/>ful for your hand also; but to
              have <lb/>the <emph style="font­-style: italic">latter</emph> without the <emph
                style="font­-style: italic">former</emph>, is
                  <choice><sic>wha</sic><corr>what</corr></choice>
              <lb/>is so foreign from my wish, that it <lb/>never can obtain my consent, I plead
              <lb/>no contract, but leave you to the free <lb/>determination of your affections.” </p>
            <p>
              <persName>CONSTANTIUS</persName> by this time, had <lb/>in some good degree recovered
              of his <lb/><choice><sic>surprize</sic><corr>surprise</corr></choice>, he encircled
              her in his arms, <lb/>and in accents of rapture exclaimed, <lb/>“O transcendantly
              propitious Hea- <lb break="no"/>ven, thrice bountiful, inexhausta- <lb break="no"
              />ble, magnificent Providence! inex- <lb break="no"/>pressibly benevolent and
              superlatively <lb/>beneficient fates! The most exalted <lb/>language is more than
              infinitely too <lb/>inexpressive to give an idea of the <lb/>grateful sensations which
              occupy my <lb/>breast, which is borne down with <lb/>the grateful sense which I have
              <lb/>of your inconceivable benediction <lb/>towards me! I arrived at the <lb/>summit
              of human gratification—I <lb/>am lost in extacy, O! ye powers <pb/>
              <lb/>omniscient, is this real, or the unsubs- <lb break="no"/>tantial fabrick of an
              empty vision? O <lb/>transcendently beneficent powers ’tis <lb/>no fiction, ’tis no
              reverie of an in- <lb break="no"/>sane mind, for I am above being <lb/>imposed on in
              this matter, I have <lb/>her in my arms the real half adora- <lb break="no"/>ble
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, propitious providence <lb/>has once more placed her
              in my <lb/>embraces, and the freeks of wild for- <lb break="no"/>tune shall never more
              separate me <lb/>from the object of my delight. No, <lb/>no, my admirable angel my
              dearest <lb/><persName>Pulchera</persName>, you have the full possession <lb/>of a
              heart totally incapable of disi- <lb break="no"/>mulation or change. No—sooner
              <lb/>than I could withdraw my supreme <lb/>affection from you, and place it on
              <lb/>another, shall the course of nature <lb/>receive a total revolution, the sun
              <lb/>shall cease to communicate light or <lb/>heat, darkness shall become the
              <lb/>medium of discerning objects—be- <lb break="no"/>lieve me, my dearest
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <choice><sic>assoon</sic><corr>as soon</corr></choice>
              <lb/>as my small affairs in <placeName>France</placeName> are set- <lb break="no"
              />tled we will cross the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName>, we <lb/>will revisit the
              land of freedom—we <lb/>will solemnize the long wished for <lb/>marriage ceremonies,
              and we will live <lb/>the remainder of our days in that fe- <lb break="no"/>licity
              which we have so long in vain <lb/>sought for. </p>
            <p> In this way they exchanged a va- <lb break="no"/>riety of mutual expressions of the
              <lb/>most fond affections, until time had <lb/>insensibly introduced the shades of
              <lb/>the evening, when <persName>Constantius</persName> again <lb/>began to think of
              his appointment <lb/>with the sister of <persName>Le Monte</persName>. He
              <lb/>mentioned to <persName>Pulchera</persName> the overtures <lb/>which he had made
              to <persName><choice><sic>Le Mont’s</sic><corr>Le Monte’s</corr></choice></persName>
              <lb/>sister, in consequence of his total- <lb break="no"/>ly despairing of ever seeing
              her <lb/>again—that a sense of honour, <lb/>made it necessary for him to re- <lb
                break="no"/>pair to his lodgings and to inform <lb/>her of his situation, and to
              make as <lb/>good terms with her as he could, <lb/>and that he would spend as little
              <lb/>time on this matter as the nature of <lb/>the thing would admit of. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Constantius</persName> then repaired to his <lb/>place of abode, where he
                  <choice><sic>fonnd</sic><corr>found</corr></choice>
              <persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName> and his sister waiting with im- <lb break="no"
              />patience and anxiety for his return; <cb/>
              <lb/>on his arrival, joy seemed to sparkle <lb/>in their countenances, but rather
              <lb/>decreased as they read in his visage <lb/>that every thing was not right in his
              <lb/>mind. However, <persName>Constantius</persName> went <lb/>thro’ the usual
              formalities of wel- <lb break="no"/>coming the lady with a tolerable <lb/>good grace.
              But he soon called <persName>Le <lb/>Monte</persName> aside, desiring to speak with
              <lb/>him alone. “My dear friend, said <lb/>he, we have long been in strict friend- <lb
                break="no"/>ship, together, which I zealously wish <lb/>to cultivate and improve,
              and there <lb/>is a matter which lays with peculiar <lb/>weight on my mind, about
              which I <lb/>wish to ask your advice, I hope you <lb/>will give me your sentiments
              fully— <lb/>speak on, quoth <persName>Le Monte</persName>, the best <lb/>of my poor
              advice is always at your <lb/>service, and you cannot lay a greater <lb/>obligation
              upon me than to command <lb/>my best services. For a considera- <lb break="no"/>ble
              time (continued <persName>Constantius</persName>) <lb/>you have been acquainted with
              my <lb/>affairs, you was no stranger to my <lb/>treaty with
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>, to the passion <lb/>I had for her, and the solemn
              obliga- <lb break="no"/>tions I was under to her, since her <lb/>exit you have been
              fully let into the <lb/>particulars of my negociations with <lb/>your amiable sister,
              and the length <lb/>to which we have carried the matter <lb/>—now Sir, supposing that
                <persName>Pulchera</persName>
              <lb/>should prove to be still alive, and <lb/>should insist on my fulfilling my en-
                <lb break="no"/>gagements, what could you advise <lb/>me to do Sir? pray dear Sir,
              on the <lb/>sacred bonds of friendship by which <lb/>we are cemented, give me your im-
                <lb break="no"/>partial opinion on the matter. </p>
            <p> “<emph style="font­-style: italic">What should you do</emph>,” reply’d
                <lb/><persName>Le Monte</persName>, can there remain a doubt <lb/>in your mind with
              regard to what <lb/>you should do? I think it is impossi- <lb break="no"/>ble there
              should—are you not a man <lb/>of honour? does not your engage- <lb break="no"/>ments,
              your solemn promises lay <lb/>with some degree of weight on your <lb/>mind? can you
              harbour an idea that <lb/>you are at liberty to break thro’ the <lb/>solemn and
              delicate obligations of a <lb/>matrimonial contract? If you do, <lb/>how can you
              answer to your own <lb/>conscience, to the wronged lady who <lb/>has placed so much
              confidence in <pb/>
              <lb/>you? can you have the most distant <lb/>idea that you can make a second con- <lb
                break="no"/>veyance of yourself to one woman be- <lb break="no"/>fore you are
              discharged from the oth- <lb break="no"/>er? can you lawfully dispose of any ar- <lb
                break="no"/>ticle, after you have conveyed away the <lb/>whole of your title to it?
              If you <lb/>cannot, I wish to be informed of the <lb/>means by which you were
              discharg- <lb break="no"/>ed from your obligations to <persName>Pulche- <lb break="no"
                />ra</persName>? will you say, you supposed she <lb/>was dead? Is that sufficient
              think <lb/>you? can your own mistake deprive <lb/>her of that right which she had to
              <lb/>you, in consequence of your volun- <lb break="no"/>tary contract? No, your good
              sense <lb/>will forbid your harbouring such un- <lb break="no"/>worthy ideas. If
                <persName>Pulchera</persName> is alive, <lb/>in the name of common justice mar- <lb
                break="no"/>ry her, your engagements to my sis- <lb break="no"/>ter must in the
              nature of things, be <lb/>on this implyed condition, that <persName>Pul- <lb
                  break="no"/>chera</persName> was no more! it was totally out <lb/>of your power to
              make any other <lb/>contract with her, whether that con- <lb break="no"/>dition was
              express or not. </p>
            <p> Well, (said <persName>Constantius</persName>) strange as <lb/>it may appear,
                <persName>Pulchera</persName> is yet alive <lb/>—I have seen her—she is now at
              <lb/>the sign of the Eagle; <persName>Le Monte</persName>
              <lb/>interrupted him, saying “Then <lb/>marry her, otherwise I should esteem <lb/>you
              as totally unworthy of any <lb/>share in my friendship—you seem to <lb/>hesitate, I
              will call in my sister—I <lb/>will inform her of the circumstances, <lb/>and then, if
              she will consent to marry <lb/>you under this predicament, I shall blush <lb/>when I
              reflect that I was ever allied <lb/>to her, and from henceforth will for- <lb
                break="no"/>ever disown her as a relation of mine. <lb/>I will call her and inform
              her, tho’ <lb/>I see by your countenance, that your <lb/>sentiments correspond with
              mine.” </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Le Monte</persName> called in his sister to <lb/>them and informed her of
              the whole <lb/>affair, who, looking on <persName/>
              <lb/>with a pleasant and very wishful <lb/>countenance, thus said: “Dear sir,
              <lb/>disappointments were never agreea- <lb break="no"/>ble to my nature, and I have
              often <lb/>thought that I had the least patience <lb/>to bear with them of any mortal
              ex- <lb break="no"/>isting, and I have not a single doubt <lb/>but my affections are
              as strong to- <cb/>
              <lb break="no"/>wards you as <persName>Pulchera’s</persName> are, yet <lb/>you are
              her’s by right, and your after <lb/>engagements to me under the mis- <lb break="no"
              />taken idea of her being dead, cannot <lb/>make her claim to you invalid, hesi- <lb
                break="no"/>tate not, my dear <persName>Constantius</persName>, fulfil <lb/>your
              engagements to her; you will <lb/>totally forfeit every claim to my af- <lb break="no"
              />fections and esteem, if you do not— <lb/>you have my most fervent prayers <lb/>that
              you may continue long and last- <lb break="no"/>ing blessings to each other in the
              <lb/>connubial state, she will always be <lb/>sure of a peculiar place in my esteem
              <lb/>for the good-will I bear to you—I <lb/>hope you will favour us by introdu- <lb
                break="no"/>cing her into our company this eve- <lb break="no"/>ning, it will afford
              me the most sen- <lb break="no"/>sible pleasure to be in any measure <lb/>instrumental
              in conducing to her hap- <lb break="no"/>piness. <persName>Constantius</persName>
              returned her <lb/>a very polite compliment, for her <lb/>candid and amiable overture,
              expres- <lb break="no"/>sing his wishes, that providence <lb/>would furnish her with
              an husband <lb/>suitable to her rank in life, and one <lb/>that would be much more
              worthy <lb/>of her than he could have the <lb/>arrogance to pretend to be; he
              <lb/>then in company with <persName>Le Monte</persName>, <lb/>waited on
                <persName>Pulchera</persName> from the sign of <lb/>the Eagle, introduced her to the
              sister <lb/>of <persName>Le Monte</persName>, where the remainder <lb/>of the evening
              was spent in the <lb/>greatest conviviality, and nothing <lb/>could exceed the
              pleasing compli- <lb break="no"/>ments, which passed between those ri- <lb break="no"
              />val ladies. </p>
            <p>
              <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Pulchera</persName>, after <lb/>this,
              made the greatest dispatch pos- <lb break="no"/>sible in their preparations, for re-
                <lb break="no"/>turning home, and in about one <lb/>weeks time, they embarked
              accord- <lb break="no"/>ingly, taking an affectionate farewel <lb/>of <persName>Le
                Monte</persName> and his sister, and <lb/>after a short and pleasant passage,
              <lb/>they arrived safely at <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, <lb/>and on the same
              day repaired to her <lb/>father’s house. The shock was al- <lb break="no"/>most too
              great for her father’s <lb/>nerves, he embraced them both ex- <lb break="no"
              />tatically—asking a thousand pardons <lb/>for his misconduct towards them, <lb/>and
              with tears of joy promised to <lb/>devote the remainder of his days to <pb/>
              <lb/>the substantiating their happiness, <lb/>about a week from this, they joined
              <lb/>their hands at the altar of <seg xml:id="a048" corresp="#n048"
                  ><persName>Hymen</persName>,</seg><note xml:id="n048" corresp="#a048"><term
                  style="font-style: italic"><persName>Hymen</persName></term>: the god of marriage
                in Greek mythology.</note>
              <lb/>amidst a croud of spectators, whose <lb/>pleased countenances bespoke the
              <lb/>inward joy of their hearts, and they <lb/>now live the greatest ornaments of
              <lb/>the married state. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
  </text>
</TEI>
